<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The guilty-covered clergy-man unvailed; in a plain and candid reply unto two bundles of wrath and confusion, wrapt up in one and twenty sheets of paper. The one written by Christopher Fowler and Simon Ford of Reading; the other by William Thomas of Ubley in Somersetshire. Wherein all their malicious slanders and false accusations, which they cast upon the truth, are clean wash'd off; their weapons with which they war against the Lamb, broken over their own heads; and they, with the rest of the tyth-exacting teachers, proved to be the great incendaries, and mis-leaders of these nations. In which also there is made a brief and sober application, to the magistrates, and other inhabitants, within the city of Bristol. / By Thomas Speed, a friend to all that tremble at the Word of the Lord; but an irreconcileable enemy to the mysterious deceit, and monstrous hypocrisie of those that do teach for hire, and divine for money.</title>
            <author>Speed, Thomas, b. 1622 or 3.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93646</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E893_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203614</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863510</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863510</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168420</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93646)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168420)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 134:E893[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The guilty-covered clergy-man unvailed; in a plain and candid reply unto two bundles of wrath and confusion, wrapt up in one and twenty sheets of paper. The one written by Christopher Fowler and Simon Ford of Reading; the other by William Thomas of Ubley in Somersetshire. Wherein all their malicious slanders and false accusations, which they cast upon the truth, are clean wash'd off; their weapons with which they war against the Lamb, broken over their own heads; and they, with the rest of the tyth-exacting teachers, proved to be the great incendaries, and mis-leaders of these nations. In which also there is made a brief and sober application, to the magistrates, and other inhabitants, within the city of Bristol. / By Thomas Speed, a friend to all that tremble at the Word of the Lord; but an irreconcileable enemy to the mysterious deceit, and monstrous hypocrisie of those that do teach for hire, and divine for money.</title>
                  <author>Speed, Thomas, b. 1622 or 3.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert at the black Spread-Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to "A sober answer to an angry epistle" by Christopher Fowler and Simon Ford and "Rayling rebuked" by William Thomas.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 18".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fowler, Christopher, 1610?-1678. --  Sober answer to an angry epistle --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ford, Simon, 1619?-1699 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Thomas, William, 1593-1667. --  Rayling rebuked --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168420:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ILTY-COVERED</hi> CLERGY-MAN <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NVAILED;</hi> IN A plain and candid REPLY unto Two Bundles of Wrath and Confuſion, wrapt up in One and twenty ſheets of Paper.</p>
            <p>THE ONE Written by <hi>Chriſtopher Fowler</hi> and <hi>Simon Ford</hi> of <hi>Reading;</hi> The other by <hi>William Thomas</hi> of <hi>Ubley</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein all their malicious Slanders and falſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations, which they caſt upon the Truth, are clean waſh'd off; Their weapons with which they war againſt the Lamb, broken over their own heads; and they, with the reſt of the Tyth-exacting Teachers, proved to be the great Incendaries, and Miſ-leaders of theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>In which alſo there is made a brief and ſober Application, to the Magiſtrates, and other Inhabitants, within the City of <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS SPEED,</hi> a Friend to all that <hi>tremble at the Word of the Lord;</hi> But an irreconcileable Enemy to the myſterious Deceit, and monſtrous Hypocriſie of thoſe that do <hi>Teach for Hire,</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine for Money.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 10.21.</hi>
               </bibl> The Pastors are become BR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TISH, and have not ſought the Lord, therefore they ſhall not proſper, and all their <hi>Flock</hi> ſhall be SCATTERED.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Sence. Tragoed.</hi>
               </bibl> Sequitur ſuperbos ulter à tergo Deus.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Juven. Sat. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>— nihileſt audacius illis</l>
               <l>Deprenſis, iram atquè animos à Crimine ſumunt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the black Spread-Eagle at the weſt end of <hi>Pauls</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:168420:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168420:2"/>
            <head>To the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> now aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I dare not give you flattering Titles, with the pen of a <hi>Sycophant;</hi> yet I can truly ſay that I love you (as you abide in the fear of the Lord) with the heart of a <hi>plain-dealing</hi> friend.<note place="margin">Job. 32.22.</note> Its recorded in the Scriptures of truth, that imperious <hi>Haman</hi> (fluſh'd with his advance to his <hi>ſhort-lived</hi> honor) did ſtrenuouſly endeavor to have cut off the necks of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of innocent Jews, upon <hi>Mordecaies ſtiff</hi> knee: The murderous deſign being laid, the ſubtle old ſerpent that <hi>ruled</hi> in this man of blood, was not to ſeek of an expedient to bring it into execution. Let but the Kings <hi>approbation</hi> and <hi>Decree</hi> be obtained, and then this proud Courtier maketh ſure, of ſatisfying that luſt upon the Jews <hi>throats,</hi> which he could by no means effect upon <hi>Mordecaies knee.</hi> To this end <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> his ears muſt be filled with ſuggeſtions, as full of <hi>falſhood</hi> as <hi>malice.</hi> Theſe <hi>harmles</hi> people are ſlanderouſly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to him, to be very evil members of his body politick;<note place="margin">Eſt. 3.8</note> both by reaſon of the <hi>diverſity</hi> of their <hi>Laws from all other people,</hi> and alſo their <hi>diſobedience to the Kings Laws.</hi> And therefore it could not well conſiſt with the <hi>Kings profit,</hi> to indulge to ſuch a <hi>heterodox</hi> generation (within any of his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces</hi>) the benefit of breathing in the common air.</p>
            <p>Although <hi>Haman</hi> be dead, yet that <hi>foul spirit</hi> by which he was acted, ſurvived him throughout all generations, unto this very day: When Chriſt the <hi>Sun of righteouſneſs,</hi> began
<pb facs="tcp:168420:3"/>to riſe in the <hi>brightneſs</hi> of his glory, and ſo out ſhine the <hi>faint</hi> glory of all the Jewiſh <hi>Rites, Worſhips, Services;</hi> the <hi>Rulers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.4.</note> 
               <hi>Prieſts, Scribes, Phariſees,</hi> and the people alſo (by the <hi>Chief-Prieſts</hi> perſwaſion) conſpire his death. The <hi>life</hi> appeareth, but the <hi>letter</hi> would deſtroy it; the power is brought forth, but the form ſtandeth ready to devour it. But Chriſt is <hi>innocent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.22.</note> there being <hi>no guile found in his mouth.</hi> And therefore ſince he cannot be impeach'd (as an evil doer) for matter of <hi>fact,</hi> he muſt for matter of <hi>Opinion, Judgement, Principles.</hi> Although he hath <hi>done</hi> no evil (being in his converſation <hi>holy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.26. Mat. 26, 61.</note> 
               <hi>harmleſs, undefiled, and ſeparate from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi>) yet it is by them preſumed that he <hi>thinketh</hi> evil, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they judge him to have <hi>ſpoken</hi> evil, <hi>viz.</hi> dangerous words about their Temple,<note place="margin">Verſ. 65.</note> nay <hi>blaſphemous</hi> words againſt God; and therefore (by the conſent of <hi>Prieſt-ridden Pilat</hi>) he is hurried to the croſs to ſuffer as a <hi>Deceiver.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Is there any <hi>new thing under the Sun?</hi> Is not the ſame ſpirit of pride, and perſecution (clothed in the <hi>garb</hi> of ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing zeal) found walking openly in the ſtreets of our <hi>Cities, Towns,</hi> and <hi>Villages</hi> at this day? Are not the innocent (now as of old) traduced to you both by <hi>Preſs</hi> and <hi>Pulpit,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notions of <hi>Quakers, Hereticks, Blaſphemers,</hi> and <hi>Deceivers?</hi> And where malice cannot reach them as tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors of the <hi>Civil Law</hi> (being thereunto obedient <hi>for conſcience ſake</hi>) are they not (with <hi>Daniel</hi>) enſnared <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the law of their God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 6.5.</note> Have not the impetuous inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of the <hi>Pulpit</hi> of late, had that <hi>deſtructive</hi> influence upon many in authority, that (contrary to the <hi>righteous</hi> law of this Nation) it hath been made matter of <hi>crime</hi> unto many <hi>peaceably</hi> to travel upon the high ways? Nay have not ſeveral perſons,<note place="margin">One and twenty in a few days ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up by ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med guards and ſent to <hi>Exon</hi> Goal, of which one di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there.</note> that have been conſtantly faithful to the States intereſt, been violently ſurpriſed, as they were travelling about their lawful occaſions, and caſt into <hi>bonds,</hi> among <hi>Rogues,</hi> and <hi>Felons,</hi> for no other tranſgreſſion but this, that they did <hi>own</hi> but the <hi>name,</hi> or the <hi>perſon,</hi> of one that is called a <hi>Quaker?</hi> An unheard of inrode upon the liberties of Engliſh men; and a practice rarely to be parallel'd in the times of the foreſt perſecutions that hiſtory maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of;</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:168420:3"/>
            <p>It's ſtoried of <hi>Marcus Aurelius Antoninus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. Hiſt.</note> a Roman Emperor, that (in the time of the fourth perſecution of the Chriſtians) being reduced to a great <hi>exigent,</hi> both becauſe he and his Army were ſtreightly environed by their enemies in the midſt of Germany, and had alſo wanted <hi>freſh water</hi> for the ſpace of <hi>five</hi> daies. And having called (but in vain) upon his <hi>Country Gods</hi> for relief, he ſendeth for a number of Chriſtians; againſt whom (at their firſt approach) he was not a little <hi>enraged,</hi> for that they came (ſaith <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus</hi> himſelf) without either <hi>Weapon, Munition, Armor,</hi> or <hi>Trumpets, as men abhorring ſuch preparation, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture, but only ſatisfied in truſt of their God, whom they carry about with them in their CONSCIENCES.</hi> Theſe, <hi>falling proſtrate upon the ground, prayed to a God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NKNOWN of me;</hi> upon which there <hi>fell pleaſant ſhowres</hi> upon <hi>Antoninus</hi> his hoſt, but a <hi>ſtorm of hail mixed with much lightning,</hi> upon the hoſt of his enemies; by which means it came to paſs, that <hi>he,</hi> and <hi>his,</hi> were <hi>refreſhed,</hi> and his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries <hi>diſcomfited.</hi> Whereupon he writeth an expreſs to the Senate and people of <hi>Rome,</hi> in theſe words; <hi>If any ſhall apprehend one that is a Chriſtian, only for that cauſe, I will that he being apprehended, may without puniſhment have leave to confeſs the ſame, ſo that there be none other cauſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt him, but that he is a Chriſtian; but let his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer be burned alive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I write not this (the Lord is my witneſs) as deſiring fire from heaven, upon thoſe that thirſt after mine own, and the blood of thouſands in this Nation, becauſe we cannot wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the <hi>image,</hi> which they would ſet up; but only to mind you, that, even among the <hi>heathens,</hi> it was deemed <hi>unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,</hi> that, where mens converſations were otherwiſe <hi>honeſt</hi> (being compared with the <hi>juſt</hi> laws of men) they ſhould notwithſtanding ſuffer for what they did <hi>beleeve,</hi> and <hi>practice, concerning the law of their God.</hi> Nor is it my deſign to blunt the edge of the ſword againſt the <hi>tranſgreſſor.</hi> The <hi>righteous</hi> law was made for the <hi>unrighteous</hi> perſon,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.9.</note> and upon him doth the ſtroak thereof <hi>juſtly</hi> fall. Whilſt your ſword is born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>evil doer,</hi> its the ſword of the Lord: But beware
<pb facs="tcp:168420:4"/>of turning the edge thereof againſt the <hi>innocent;</hi> for then its no longer the ſword of <hi>God,</hi> but the executioner of your own <hi>lusts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do well know how paſſionatly ye are invocated (by thoſe that long to be in the <hi>Chair</hi>) to enact Laws to eſtabliſh <hi>Church Government</hi> (as they call it) and puniſh <hi>Hereticks;</hi> that is, in plain Engliſh, to make every <hi>Pariſh Teacher</hi> a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> to give Laws to yours and other mens <hi>conſciences.</hi> Neither am I ignorant with what longing expectation, many that call themſelves Miniſters of Chriſt (though none of his Miniſters ever perſecuted any man) do wait to receive Commiſſion from you, to exerciſe the matchleſs cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that villanous Tyrant, in ſtretching all that are too <hi>ſhort</hi> to the juſt length of their <hi>bed,</hi> and cutting all thoſe <hi>ſhorter</hi> who in length do <hi>exceed</hi> it. But however they may inceſſantly urge you (pretending a <hi>viſion from the Lord</hi>) to eſtabliſh laws to bind the conſcience; yet know, that it's Chriſts prerogative to give laws to that; and you will be in <hi>his</hi> eſteem but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> whilſt you undertake to <hi>rule</hi> there,<note place="margin">O. P. In his Speech to the Parl. in the painted Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. <hi>Sept.</hi> 12. 1654.</note> where he is of right <hi>ſole King,</hi> and <hi>Law giver.</hi> He ſpake truth, who ſaid, <hi>That liberty of conſcience is a NAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAL right.</hi> So that he that maketh an intrenchment upon that, doth (what in him lieth) bereave me of my <hi>birth right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sirs, Deceive not your ſelves, nor let the lips of any <hi>falſe Prophet</hi> deceive you;<note place="margin">Page 30.</note> for I ſay plainly to you (and you ſhall one day witneſs what I ſay to be true) that it will neither be for your <hi>honor,</hi> or your <hi>peace</hi> in the <hi>great day</hi> of your account, that any Act ſhall be found enrolled among the Laws of <hi>your</hi> eſtabliſhing, whereby the <hi>holy one of Iſrael</hi> hath been ſought to be limited Which of you <hi>can mean ſure the waters</hi> of the great deep <hi>in the hollow of his hand?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 40.12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>or mete out heaven with his ſpan, or comprehend the duſt of the earth in a meaſure, or weigh the mountains in ſcales, and the hills in a ballance?</hi> Or which of you <hi>hath at any time di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the Spirit of the Lord, or being his counſellor hath taught him?</hi> O how then is it, that you ſhould but once think to <hi>pale</hi> and <hi>limit</hi> (within the ſcant circumference of mans cloudy reaſon) that Sovereign <hi>WIND,</hi> which bloweth <hi>when,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:168420:4"/>
               <hi>where,</hi> and <hi>how</hi> it liſteth?<note place="margin">Gen. 17.14.</note> There is a time when <hi>circumciſion</hi> is commanded upon pain of <hi>death;</hi> there is a ſeaſon when the <hi>ſame</hi> thing maketh Chriſt <hi>unprofitable</hi> to the uſer.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.2.</note> There is a time when <hi>ſwearing by the name of the Lord</hi> is commanded;<note place="margin">Deut. 6.13.</note> and there is a time when the great <hi>Law-giver</hi> (whom under penalty of being <hi>deſtroyed</hi> we are commanded to hear) cuteth off all exceptions, and ſaith <hi>ſwear not at all.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 3.23. Matth. 5.34. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> "ΟΛΩΣ.</note> Take heed of <hi>forbidding</hi> where Chriſt <hi>commandeth,</hi> and of <hi>commanding</hi> where he <hi>forbiddeth.</hi> In the counſel of the Lord ſtand, and you will find direction near you. The hand of grace doth hold the <hi>candle</hi> of the Lord (a meaſure of the <hi>light</hi> of Chriſt which you have received) in all your Conſciences;<note place="margin">Joh. 8.12.</note> being guided by which, you will be ſafely led on to enact laws (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that <hi>Royal</hi> law written in the heart) <hi>for</hi> God, and not <hi>againſt</hi> him. At this Oracle, the ſpiritual light of Chriſt (ſo deſpiſed by the <hi>wiſe</hi> among men) you may take counſel in your greateſt ſtreights, and find certain reſolution. You ſhall neither ſtagger nor err, for its conduct is in the <hi>ſure</hi> and <hi>clean</hi> paths of peace, not contrary, but according to the Scriptures of truth, which were given forth by the <hi>holy men of God,</hi> who dwelt in the ſame light of Jeſus. Take heed of acting that thing for which the <hi>witneſs</hi> of God in your conſciences do condemn you; for if that condemn you, <hi>God is greater then the conſcience.</hi> Finally, Remember that whilſt you abide faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful with the Lord, <hi>he will be with you,</hi> but if you <hi>forſake him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 28 9. Iſa. 59.10.</note> he will <hi>forſake you;</hi> and then you will be left to <hi>grope as in</hi> the dark at <hi>noon day,</hi> and <hi>ſtagger in your counſels as a drunken man ſtaggereth in his vomit.</hi> And know,<note place="margin">Iſa. 19.14.</note> that as all powers in this nation have ſtood firm, whilſt they ſtood for God ſo it hath been, and will be, the certain fore-runner of their ſudden <hi>ruine,</hi> when once they begin to <hi>claſh,</hi> or <hi>contend,</hi> with the <hi>Lord,</hi> or his <hi>people.</hi> The Lord God Almighty be your <hi>ſun</hi> and <hi>your ſhield.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am <hi>Yours in the love and ſervice of the Lamb againſt the Dragon. THOMAS SPEED.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:168420:5"/>
            <head>To the honeſt Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have now (through the croud of my other neceſſary imployments) brought forth this enſuing Reply, to Two large and fiery Pamphlets, both written in Anſwer to a ſhort Epistle, directed to the publick Teachers of this Nation. The after part of one of which, written by <hi>Chriſtopher Fowler</hi> and <hi>Simon Ford,</hi> concerneth not the ſaid Epiſtle, but the Book to which it was prefixed, and therefore to that I have not now made my Reply,<note place="margin">In the Epiſtle to his Reader.</note> being threatned with a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Anſwer to the whole Book by <hi>William Thomas,</hi> and then I ſhall Reply upon them both together. Or in caſe of <hi>William Thomas</hi> his ſilence, I ſhall then undertake them ſingly; nothing doubting but that in the ſtrength of truth, by the power of the Lord, I ſhall be made able to repel all the furious aſſaults which they therein make, upon the Lamb's followers. In the mean while, having once caſt thine eye upon this enſuing Reply, be at the expence of ſo much pains as to read it through; leſt by a curſory or partial view thereof, thou ſhouldeſt wrong me or mine Adverſaries. Whilſt thou art reading ſhut prejudice out of doors, and ſet ſingleneſs, and ſobriety, as Watchmen at the door<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſts of thy heart, to keep it out; ſo wilt thou be kept from paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing raſh or unrighteous judgment upon the truth, or me. The God of Wiſdom give thee <hi>underſtanding in all things.</hi> Farewel.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THOMAS SPEED.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168420:5"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Guilty-covered Clergy-man <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nvail'd,</hi> In a Reply to two Pamphlets, The One, Written by <hi>Chriſtopher Fowler,</hi> and <hi>Simon Ford</hi> of <hi>Redding.</hi> The Other, By <hi>William Thomas</hi> of <hi>Ubley</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Chriſtopher Fowler,</hi> and <hi>Simon Ford,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>UPon the ſixteenth day of the moneth paſt (called <hi>July</hi>) I received (by the hands of a Friend) a Pamphlet with a ſcoffing inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on written upon it, ſubſcribed with both your hands, and directed to my ſelf, which I have peruſed, and ſeriouſly weighed, and do find it to be a monſtrous birth, begotten by the Prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, conceived in the womb of your own guilt, and brought forth by the vigorous aſſiſtance of that great <hi>Red Dragon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 12.4, 5.</note> which ſtood <hi>before the Woman ready to be delivered, to devour her man child, as ſoon as it was born.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since which time, I have met with another heap of anger, and confuſion, come forth under the name of <hi>WILLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AM THOMAS</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bley;</hi> a piece which is found having on it, the ſame ſtamp of enmity with yours, onely with this difference, that whereas <hi>you</hi> have ſubtilly couche,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168420:6"/>and covered your malice under the deceitful paint of ſmooth words, <hi>he</hi> hath thrown out his ſcorn, and diſdain, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth, and mine own perſon, under a thinner co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, in the view of all men.</p>
            <p>To both theſe Pamphlets, I ſhall now apply my ſelf in a way of Reply; not thereby to gratifie either of your wills, or luſts, nor to vindicate my ſelf, who could (the Lord is my witneſs) gladly ſit down in ſilence, wearing your reproaches as a crown upon my head, and (through the power of <hi>his grace</hi> who hath ſaved me) eſteem it my honour, not onely to <hi>ſuffer affliction,</hi> but to <hi>die,</hi> (bearing teſtimony againſt their wickedneſs) under the <hi>mercileſs</hi> hands of your <hi>bloody</hi> genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But for the <hi>truths</hi> ſake which you ſo prophanely <hi>trample</hi> upon, and for the <hi>innocents</hi> ſake whoſe blood you ſo eagerly <hi>thirſt</hi> after, and for the <hi>ſimples</hi> ſake whom you ſo miſerably <hi>delude,</hi> I may not keep ſilence. But before I ſpeak either to the Title or the Contents of either of your Papers, I ſhall premiſe theſe five things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In my Reply, I ſhall principally direct my Speech to you two, yet ſo as that I ſhall in paſſing on take notice, of what ever <hi>William Thomas</hi> hath ſpoken<note n="*" place="margin">Which is but very little.</note> 
                  <hi>worthy</hi> of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. Who in his Epiſtle directed to the Reader, and prefixed to his Pamphlet, declareth his reſolutions to <hi>have no further to do with me;</hi> although in his following Book there be ſcarce a Page, in which he doth not mention me with ſcorn and contempt.<note place="margin">☞</note> A rare demonſtration of his <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity!</hi> to throw as many ſtones at me as the hand of his <hi>rage</hi> could well lay hold on, having but juſt before told his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that he would <hi>have no more to do with me.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 Take notice, that I ſhall not make it my buſineſs to trace you in every <hi>unſavory</hi> and <hi>impertinent</hi> expreſſion throughout your Books. I eſteem my time more precious, then to ſquander it away in raking into all that <hi>mire</hi> and <hi>dirt,</hi> that's cloſed up in thoſe one and twenty ſheets of paper; However you may eſteem of <hi>time,</hi> who live by the ſweat of other mens brows, <hi>eating the fat, and drinking the ſweet;</hi> with me, I muſt let you know, it's more precious then plenty.</item>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:168420:6"/>
               <item>3 What ever of <hi>dung</hi> or <hi>filth,</hi> you have caſt on the truth or my ſelf, I ſhall quietly wipe off, not lifting it back again upon your own faces, but let it fall into the Channel, whence you may perhaps ſpend your ſpare hours to take it again, to beſpatter the <hi>innocent</hi> with in you next.</item>
               <item>4 Whether it may prove an irritation, or an allay to your fury, I am not ſolicitous, but from me you may not expect <hi>flattering</hi> language: As the Scripture doth, ſo ſhall I ſtudy to give every thing its true denomination, by calling a <hi>lie, deceit, hypocrifie,</hi> by their proper names; which I prefume you will judge <hi>railing,</hi> but I (according to the Scripture) plainneſs.</item>
               <item>5 Whereas throughout that Epiſtle (which ſticks ſo ſorely as an arrow in your <hi>guilty</hi> breaſts) I did ſpeak to thoſe of your Function under the name of <hi>Teachers,</hi> waving that of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> being willing to cut off every ſhadow of a juſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, now I ſhall occaſionally make uſe thereof, in this my following Reply, and that for theſe two Reaſons.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe your ſelves do own the name, and do call your ſelves and your Brethren thereby in page 13. at the cloſe of the 12 Section of your Book: So that you cannot rationally take it ill that I give you what you take to your ſelves.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe you lay confident claim to their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance <hi>(viz.) Tythes,</hi> which the Miniſters of the Goſpel, ſent out by Jeſus never claimed; and therefore it's but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, that a diſtinction ſhould be kept betwixt you and them, as well in your names as practices.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being premiſed, I ſhall paſs on to your Books. To both which, I muſt juſtly charge you with prefixing <hi>lying</hi> Titles: <hi>You</hi> ſay, <hi>A ſober Anſwer to an angry Epiſtle;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as neither was my Epiſtle <hi>angry,</hi> nor your Anſwer <hi>ſober;</hi> as all that live in lobriety will (upon peruſal of both) truly judge. You had ſhewed ſome honeſty in ſpeaking truth, if you had <hi>(vice verſâ)</hi> ſaid, <hi>An angry Anſwer to a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Epiſtle. William Thomas</hi> is more notorious in his —tranſgreſſing the limits both of truth and honeſty, calling his bundle of ignorance and paſſion, by the name of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168420:7"/>
               <hi>Railing rebuked:</hi> A ſwelling Title, thinking thereby to beget his reader into a beleif, that he had to do with ſome monſter of a man.</p>
            <p>What a furious peice is a guilty Prieſt when his ſore is rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed? Let truth hit him but upon the ſeat of his guilt, and you rouſe a Lyon from his ſleep. In what a ſtrange Region of flattery, and filthy complements, do thoſe men breath, with whom <hi>truth</hi> in plainneſs of ſpeech, is <hi>railing,</hi> and the expreſs language of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> reviling?</p>
            <p>You proceed in your Title page to charge me with <hi>revolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from</hi> being <hi>a publick Teacher, to merchandize.</hi> To which I reply, that the underſtanding Reader may eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, how far your Book is from being a <hi>ſober Anſwer,</hi> when as you have the confidence to prefix ſo egregious a lie in the very front of it. For that thoſe that know my manner of life can teſtifie, that for many years together, whilſt I was a <hi>Publick teacher</hi> (as you ſtile me) <hi>I did merchandize;</hi> and therefore did not <hi>revolt</hi> from the one to the other. That I am ſtill a <hi>Merchant</hi> is true, in which calling I eſteem it my duty to abide faithful, not making my ſelf burthenſom unto others, as your troubleſome generation are to the whole Nation at this day. So far am I from eſteeming the name of a <hi>Merchant,</hi> a term of reproach to me, that I do in heart prefer one <hi>honeſt Merchant,</hi> before a legion of <hi>Tithe-exacting</hi> Prieſts; and muſt withall tell you, that, did the Commonwealth reap no greater yeatly advantage from the <hi>induſtrious</hi> Merchant, then it doth from the <hi>devouring</hi> Prieſts, they that ſit at Helm might at each years end, write down their names, in the books of their greateſt accompts, in <hi>worthleſs</hi> Cyphers.</p>
            <p>You charge me further, with uſing <hi>Jeſuitical equivocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> This is a ſtone that every <hi>ſorry thing in black</hi> (to uſe your own expreſſion) hath to caſt in his face, who hath ſo much honeſty and courage, as to bear teſtimony againſt the wickedneſs of your Phariſaicall generation. If any man doth appear with ſtrength of truth and plainneſs, to decry the deceit and unrighteouſneſs of teachers and people; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ignorant Prieſt is preſently crying out a <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> a <hi>Jeſuite,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:168420:7"/>thinking by that brand of reproach, to render thoſe <hi>juſt</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations that are brought againſt them, leſs credible in the judgements of the <hi>ſimple.</hi> But do not decieve your ſelves, in thinking that I ſhall be ſcared from diſcovering your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, by your great words, I am as irreconcileable an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſt, to the Antichriſtian principles, and practices, found among the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> as I am to the <hi>ſame</hi> found among you; from declaring againſt which, I ſhall never be diſſwaded by either <hi>bribe</hi> or <hi>fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reſt of your ſcorns, and unſavory ſcoffs in your Title page, I paſs over, as being unwilling to defile my thoughts, or my pen, with ſuch filthy rubbiſh. I now paſs to both your Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>And firſt, I cannot but take notice how you walk in the old path of begging <hi>Patronage</hi> to your <hi>deformed</hi> Pamphlet.<note place="margin">Chriſt. Fowler <hi>and</hi> Simon Ford<hi>'s Epiſtle to Col.</hi> Syden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, <hi>exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
               </note> You have ſome mire and dirt to throw upon the innocent, out of the <hi>raging Sea</hi> of your inward guilt, and what then? that you may act your deſign with the more authority, you muſt crouch and cringe to Col. <hi>Sydenham,</hi> and tell him that you are his <hi>Honors affectionate Servants,</hi> that under his <hi>ſhelter</hi> (as you phraſe it) you might ſhoot out the bitter ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of <hi>lies</hi> and <hi>ſlanders</hi> (with which your Epiſtle and Book do abound) with the greater hope of credit, among thoſe that live in the ſame ſpirit of wickedneſs with your ſelves. Had you writ nought but truth, that would not have needed the ſhadow of any mans wing for its <hi>ſhelter,</hi> and <hi>patronage.</hi> I once knew Colonel <hi>Sydenham</hi> dwelling in a ſpirit of <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> and <hi>moderation,</hi> in which if he yet abideth, and be not Prieſt-ridden into paſſion, and prejudice againſt the truth (which I ſhould be ſorry to underſtand) I doubt not but he doth diſcern and loath that ſpirit of <hi>fawning</hi> and <hi>flattery</hi> upon which you offered up to him that <hi>polluted</hi> ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of an Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>You begin it with a high (but a lying) Accuſation charging me with <hi>Apoſtacy to damnable doctrines;</hi> To which I ſay, That he that ſaith that of me which he neither doth, nor can prove, is a lyar; and ſuch do I charge you Two to be, who have moſt maliciouſly dealt with me both in this Epiſtle and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168420:8"/>the Pamphlet, as your Predeceſſors (the <hi>Roman</hi> blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuckers) did with the poor innocent Chriſtians in thoſe days, <hi>viz. cloath</hi> them with the skins of ſome <hi>ugly</hi> creature, and then caſt them to the <hi>wild beaſt</hi> to be devoured. But I doubt not, but that I ſhall (before you and I part) give the ſober Reader a <hi>true</hi> repreſentation of ſuch <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> of yours and your Brethrens, as will make his ears to <hi>tingle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You tell Colonel <hi>Sydenham</hi> that in my Epiſtle I <hi>chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged all the publick Teachers in the Nation, and you in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Now whether this be true or like the former, Col. <hi>Sydenham,</hi> and all honeſt readers may determine, upon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal of my Epiſtle, in which there is not a word of any chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, or any thing like it: But how doth it appear that I did <hi>challenge</hi> you? your proof is becauſe (you ſay) <hi>I ſent you each a Book by name.</hi> To which I ſhall onely ſay, That the perſon that delivered you a book from me, utterly miſtook me. For why I ſhould particularly direct a book to either of you, whoſe faces (to my knowledge) I never ſaw, nor ever exchanged word with you, let the reader judge. This is the pretended ground of your undertaking; but I rather judge the real riſe to be, from a mixture of your guilt and ambition, that you might at once give the world a proof of your abilities, both in painting and ſophiſtry. But your coverings are <hi>too ſhort,</hi> and to the moſt weak-fighted of the children of <hi>light,</hi> is your nakedneſs manifeſt.</p>
            <p>The next thing you ſuggeſt to Colonel <hi>Sydenham,</hi> as a motive to your undertaking, is, that you <hi>dared not to betray the truth, and the glory of the Lord Jeſus, nor the precious ſouls of the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Did not your hypocriſie ſtare in your faces, when you were penning theſe fained motives? Are you not known to live in a profeſſed enmity to the truth of Chriſt, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Saints, and yet pretend a zeal for it? Are not your converſations a <hi>ſtain</hi> to the very <hi>profeſſion</hi> of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me, by living in pride, covetouſneſs, by your perſecution, nay (what in you lieth) drawing his blood in his <hi>innocent</hi> Lambs;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168420:8"/>and yet you tender of his <hi>glory?</hi> Beſides, how can you ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve your ſelves from being <hi>betrayers</hi> of precious ſoul, who cry <hi>peace, peace, where the Lord hath ſpoken no peace;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 6.14.</note> and do <hi>ſlay the ſouls that ſhould not die,</hi> who do <hi>reach for doctrine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 13 19.</note> 
               <hi>the traditions of men,</hi> drawing poor ſouls from their true guide, to liſten to your corrupt dreams and divinations, and keeping them faſt in the ſnares of Satan, do lead them down hood winck'd into the chambers of death.</p>
            <p>I ſhall paſs from yours to <hi>William Thomas</hi> his Epiſtle,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Will. Thomas</hi> his Epiſtle to his friends. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the City of <hi>Briſtol</hi> ſcan'd.</note> in which he maketh a great cry, to little purpoſe. He directeth it to his <hi>well beloved Friends and Neighbors, in and about the City of</hi> Briſtol, <hi>thoſe in particular of his own charge, and in ſpecial thoſe that have ſadly, and dangerouſly declined from the Scripture path.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> I will not quarrel at the ſence or rather the — of this inſcription. I ſhall ſpeak to the thing intended. It ſeemeth that <hi>William Thomas</hi> hath thoſe of his own <hi>charge,</hi> that <hi>have ſadly, and dangerouſly declined from the Scripture path.</hi> And do they not therein demonſtrate themſelves, to be teachable Diſciples, in following their <hi>Paſtors</hi> practiſe? Sure I am, he is far wide from the <hi>Scripture-path,</hi> both in his principles and practice; and if you call to him for Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to prove what he ſaith, or doeth (as I have ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done) he will give you one of his own <hi>meanings,</hi> or wild <hi>deductions</hi> inſtead of Scripture; which if you refuſe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, then an out-cry is preſently made, here is one that <hi>deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> Scripture, an <hi>Heretick,</hi> an <hi>Heretick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He telleth his friends in <hi>Briſtol</hi> (among many other notorious untruths) that I will <hi>needs bee his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply</hi> As if (from a buſie minde) I had been the beginner of the preſent conteſt betwixt us.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>VVill. Thomas</hi> the beginner of the preſent Conteſt.</note> Whereas I was quietly abiding in my calling not deſigning to write, or print, any thing to him, or touching him. Neither can I ſay, but that I might have gone to my grave in <hi>ſilence,</hi> without writing or printing ought that related to him, or his vexatious genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but that he firſt began with me by writing, to which I returned him a <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>ſober</hi> Anſwe, upon which he repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168420:9"/>things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> touching me that were (as formerly I have ſaid) both <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> which reflected much upon the truth, and others that were innocent. The knowledge of which neceſſitated me to put pen to Paper, and prepare that for the <hi>Preſſe,</hi> which otherwiſe might never have come to publike view. And now that I am ingaged, I am reſolved in the ſtrength of the Lord, never to deſiſt (while I have a tongue to ſpeak or a hand to write) from diſcovering the monſtrous wickedneſs, of the Romiſh Whore, deckt with a glorious profeſſion. And when ever it be, that by the hand of violence my mouth ſhall be either <hi>ſtopped,</hi> or my Pen <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed,</hi> I ſhall then eſteem it my mercy from the Lord, to be made able and willing, to offer my <hi>life</hi> unto <hi>death,</hi> bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing witneſs againſt all the abominations of that <hi>blood-thirſty</hi> company of falſe Prophets, who in cruelty and oppreſſion both upon the <hi>bodies</hi> and <hi>conſciences,</hi> of Chriſts righteous ſervants, have exceedingly <hi>out-done</hi> their Fathers the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and the generation of evill-doers that have gone before them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Thomas</hi> farther telleth his friends that his <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> (meaning my ſelf) <hi>hath his abode in</hi> Briſtol, <hi>where many of the ſame apoſtatizing, and erroneous way with himſelf, are entertained and countenanced,</hi> which he <hi>cannot but preſent as matter of deep humiliation to that City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> A charge like to that of his brethrens of <hi>Redding;</hi> but (as to <hi>Error</hi> and <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi>) not the ſhadow of truth in it. Reader, let <hi>William Thomas</hi> appear, (and I ſhall be free to meet him) before any that are ſober in publike, or private in that City, and by the Scriptures of truth, let me be proved the <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> or he the <hi>Lier.</hi> But why is it <hi>matter of</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Religion is the pretence, but dominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the thing intended.</note> 
               <hi>humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation</hi> that I <hi>have my abode in</hi> Briſtol, <hi>and have with others entertainment and countenance?</hi> May not <hi>Thomas Speed</hi> and other peaceable Citizens abide in their <hi>proper</hi> habitations in <hi>Briſtol,</hi> as well as <hi>William Thomas</hi> in that which is <hi>none of his</hi> at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bley?</hi> What would this angry man have? doth he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire our throats ſhould be cut, or our perſons exiled, becauſe we dare not profeſſe Subjection to the imperious dictates of every Lordly Prieſt? Is it matter of humiliation that we
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168420:9"/>have the priviledge to breath in the common air?</p>
            <p>Hath he and his brethren been pulling, and preaching down Biſhops, and Tyrants, and praying and fighting for liberty of Conſcience, theſe fourteen yeare paſt? and is it now become matter of <hi>humiliation,</hi> that they that are more deſerving then themſelves (becauſe more faithful to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth) ſhould have the liberty of a quiet abode, among men, and that <hi>juſt countenance</hi> which the <hi>laws</hi> of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on do afford to all <hi>free born</hi> Engliſhmen? To what height is this proud Prieſtly ſpirit aſcending, which hath not elbow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>room enough throughout the Nation, unleſs it can juſtle all others (that in <hi>Conſcience</hi> do diſſent) out of the land of their nativity? Reader, mind what I ſhall ſay, and remember that I told thee of it before hand, that <hi>black</hi> and <hi>cloudy</hi> will that day be (and eſpecially to many profeſſors, who <hi>now</hi> ſit and laugh at <hi>others</hi> ſufferings) when as that helliſh <hi>Synodical</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, ſhall be reduced into practiſe <hi>(viz.)</hi> if any will not <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form,</hi> let them chooſe to themſelves either <hi>bonds,</hi> or <hi>baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He proceedeth in his anger, calling my Book an <hi>ugly mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter brought to Briſtol Fair.</hi> To which I reply, that it was ſo in part is confeſſed, for that which it contained of <hi>his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths, ſlanders,</hi> and <hi>contradictions,</hi> made it <hi>ſuch.</hi> Ay, but it was brought to <hi>Briſtol</hi> Fait.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reply.</hi> This is matter of great diſcontent to him: The fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and filthineſs of the prieſts muſt not be brought to too <hi>publike</hi> view. Do but <hi>honour them before the people,</hi> giving them the <hi>cap</hi> and the <hi>knee</hi> in the market-place, and you may call them by their <hi>proper</hi> names in <hi>private.</hi> But was not <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Thomas</hi> his Miſhapen Birth (to which I am now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my Reply) brought <hi>firſt to be ſhewed at</hi> Briſtol <hi>Fair?</hi> and hath not <hi>Thomas Speed,</hi> as much right to have a juſt vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the truth and himſelf, brought to that Fair, as <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Thomas</hi> hath for his heap of wrath and ſlanders (to ſay no more) to be <hi>firſt</hi> brought to the <hi>ſame</hi> place? Reader, when ever thou doſt meet with any Prieſt, that hath but ſo much ingenuity, as to <hi>give</hi> the ſame liberty he would <hi>have</hi> (for with one ſo qualified, I could never yet meet) I deſire
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168420:10"/>to hear of him, aſſuring thee that I ſhall highly eſteem of him, as far as he abideth faithful in the practice of that principle.</p>
            <p>There are <hi>two ſorts</hi> of perſons, to whom this poor enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged man addreſſeth himſelf in his Epiſtle, which is made up of groſs untruths ſlanders, clinches, <hi>cauſes, conſiderations, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, means,</hi> and ſuch other Babiloniſh ſtuffe, as his uſuall preachments are compounded of.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſort are ſuch, who (as he expreſſeth it) <hi>have held faſt thoſe things which they have received,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Who they are that the Prieſts do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem to ſtand firm.</note> 
               <hi>and heard from their teachers, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe he calleth in the precedent lines (in the third page of his Epiſtle) ſuch as have <hi>ſtood firm.</hi> The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh of which I ſhall give the Reader in theſe following par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. They in the eſtimation of theſe men do <hi>ſtand firm,</hi> who can <hi>worſhip</hi> and <hi>adore</hi> them in all companies where they come, as great Schollers, able Divines, and ſuch at whoſe lips they are to ſeek counſell.</item>
               <item>2. They that can eſteem what ever their teachers do Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterially dictate to them, as the Oracles of God; not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming to deviate therefrom, under the penalty of being reckoned among the deſpiſers of Gods <hi>meſſengers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. They that ſtand ready to become executioners of the Prieſts wrath, upon all thoſe as <hi>Hereticks,</hi> whom they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn for ſuch in their pulpits.</item>
               <item>4. He that can ſpend the firſt day of the week, devoutly liſtning to his Miniſter, crying out of pride, covetouſneſs, malice, &amp;c. and yet (finding him guilty of ſome or all the ſame crimes in his practice, the whole week following) can notwithſtanding before others that condemn him, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to cover over his wickedneſs with the vail of <hi>humane infirmity,</hi> alledging on his behalf, that the pureſt gold muſt have allowance of ſome grains, and that he is a very precious able Miniſter, albeit that he be attended with many (groſſe) failings; ſuch a man ſtandeth firm in their accompts.</item>
               <item>5. He that can drudge, and toil, and ſweat, the whole year about, making more conſcience of paying the <hi>tenths</hi> of all his labours to the Prieſts, then he doth of avoiding open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs, not daring to reſerve to himſelf a <hi>ſheaf,</hi> or a <hi>lamb,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:168420:10"/>or an <hi>egg,</hi> or a <hi>Pig,</hi> or a <hi>Gooſe,</hi> to which his Miniſter layeth claim, under the penalty of being condemned for one that does ſacrilegiouſly rob his God.</item>
               <item>6 In brief, they that have miſerably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſigned up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the <hi>deceitful</hi> guidance of their Prieſts, to ſee with <hi>their</hi> eyes, hear with <hi>their</hi> ears, and walk with <hi>their</hi> feet, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing where they bleſs, and curſing where they curſe, theſe are thoſe poor deluded hearts, which in the eſteem of <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Thomas</hi> and his brethren, do <hi>ſtand firm, and do hold faſt thoſe things which they have received from their Teachers.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The ſecond ſort of perſons, to whom he addreſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his Epiſtle, are ſuch as are <hi>revolted,</hi> and as he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it in the next page) are <hi>Godleſs, without a teaching Prieſt, and without a law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reproachful appellations of <hi>Revolter</hi> and <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> are (as I have ſaid before) ſtones that every <hi>Idol-Shepheard</hi> hath ready to caſt in the face of him, who durſt refuſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to their corrupt wills;<note place="margin">What revolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is in the eſteem of the Prieſts.</note> but whom they do particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intend (when they ſo ſpeak) the Reader may underſtand from what followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Such as have long lived under the deceitful, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſs teaching of their <hi>blind guides,</hi> do at length (through the riſing of the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs</hi> within them) come to diſcern, and deny all their falſe, hypocritical ways and worſhips; theſe are in their eſteem <hi>Back-ſliders, Revolters,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtates.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 Such as diſown all thoſe for Miniſters of Chriſt, who <hi>ſay</hi> and <hi>do</hi> not, bearing teſtimony againſt all Preachers and Profeſſors who (glorying in the <hi>form</hi>) are ſtrangers to the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of godlineſs.</item>
               <item>3 Such as (knowing they muſt beleeve for themſelves, becauſe die for themſelves, and account to the Lord for themſelves) do refuſe to own the <hi>dumb hirelings,</hi> as Dictators to their faith, Lords over their conſciences, or guids to their precious and immortal ſouls.</item>
               <item>4 Such who finding them that call themſelves Chriſts Miniſters, to be out of Chriſts Doctrine, builders of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:168420:11"/>and enemies to Chriſts croſs, dare not <hi>put into their mouthes,</hi> nor feed them with the Tenth of all their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe:</item>
               <item>5 If any Magiſtrate there be who hath been fierce, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in executing the Prieſts decrees againſt the innocent, but doth at laſt <hi>return</hi> to himſelf and conſider, that he hath to do onely with the regulating of the <hi>outward man,</hi> but Chriſt onely is to ſit, and <hi>rule</hi> in the Throne of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and give laws to she inward man, and thereupon doth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to intrench upon Chriſts <hi>Prerogative,</hi> by perſecuting any man for conſcience-ſake; refuſing to hang and draw, where the Prieſts do pronounce ſentence of condemnation, I ſay ſuch a Magiſtrate ſhall ſoon have a troop of Prieſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his ears, crying out a <hi>Revolter,</hi> an <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> an <hi>Apoſtate.</hi> Their Feaſting houſes, and their Pulpits, ſhall ring of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting man, as if he were a perſon rejected of God, and to be deſpiſed by men.</item>
               <item>6 Take a man that liveth in the vanity, and ſinful cuſtoms, and perhaps the prophaneneſs of the world, if he can but cry up the Prieſts, and decry thoſe that deny them, if he can but <hi>feed</hi> them and <hi>feaſt</hi> them, and <hi>admire</hi> them as able Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines; ſuch a man ſhall be bleſſed by them as an <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and <hi>a firm ſtanding</hi> Chriſtian; but if the ſame perſon (by the ſhining of the glorious light of Chriſt in his heart) come to deny the folly, and filthineſs of his former converſation, and to witneſs redemption from the <hi>vanities,</hi> and <hi>ſinful cuſtoms,</hi> of this preſent evil world, and thereupon doth bear teſtimony againſt the ſame unrighteouſneſs, found among thoſe <hi>Teachers</hi> that formerly had him in eſteem, preſently he is branded with <hi>revolting</hi> and <hi>apoſtacy,</hi> as one given over to deceit, and ſtrong deluſion.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Now if after all this, this very man (ſo changed) can be but prevailed with,<note place="margin">rindx;</note> by the ſubtilty of Satan, and the wiles of the Prieſts, to return to his former <hi>vomit,</hi> and <hi>wallow</hi> in the <hi>mire</hi> he once lay in, crying out he was <hi>deceived</hi> and <hi>deluded,</hi> ſubjecting himſelf again to the guidance and government of his former Teachers, he ſhall preſently be cried up to be a <hi>raiſed</hi> and a <hi>recovered</hi> man; though indeed, he be onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:168420:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>ſeven fold more the child of Satan,</hi> then he was in his firſt condition. Theſe things I write not upon hear-ſay, but upon certain knowledge, grounded upon ſtrict and ſerious obſervation; and who ſo are not blinded, with paſſion and prejudice againſt the truth, or do not ſhut their eyes at noon day, may ſee ſad and frequent demonſtrations of the truth of what I have now written, before their faces.</p>
            <p>What tender heart is there that doth not lament to hear the Teachers of this Nation, generally crying out to their congregations, which oftentimes do conſiſt of proud men, covetous men, malicious men; nay, drunkards, ſwearers and prophane men, charging them to take heed that they be not <hi>ſeduced and deceived by Hereticks.</hi> Whereas, what have ſuch poor hearts to be deceived of but their <hi>iniquities?</hi> And who are thoſe Hereticks they muſt beware of, but ſuch as (in love to their precious ſouls) would be inſtrumental to pull them out of their ſins, and abominations, and pluck them from out of the <hi>ſnares,</hi> in the which they are held captive, by the lying viſions, and the ſtrong deluſions, of their <hi>Idol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhepheards?</hi> Thus much touching the two ſorts of perſons to whom this Epiſtle is directed.</p>
            <p>As to the matter of it, it's principally made up of <hi>malice,</hi> and <hi>ſlanders,</hi> partly out of his own creating, and partly of ſuch as he hath borrowed from others, that are of his confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy, and live in the ſame ſpirit of violence and bitterneſs with himſelf. With which is intermixed his grave paſtoral advice, to his <hi>Friends and neighbors in and about the City of Briſtol</hi> to <hi>ſtand firm;</hi> that is in plain Engliſh, to continue in darkneſs, paſſing away their few daies in a pleaſing dream of happineſs, admiring their Teachers, putting into their mouths, receiving what drops from their lips for divine O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, and in the cloſe to bid defiance, and offer all manner of injury to ſuch as would awaken them out of that ſleep of death, into which they are rock'd by thoſe fair-ſpeaking de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers of their ſouls.</p>
            <p>Towards the concluſion of his tedious Sermon, preach'd in his Epiſtle, he propoſeth his laſt <hi>means of revocation of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted Chriſtians</hi> (as he expreſſeth it) <hi>viz.</hi> that they <hi>would
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168420:12"/>come again to prayer and faſting</hi> Urging this as his motive, <hi>for that would caſt out all evils and Devils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> If this be true, why then is it that <hi>all evils and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils</hi> are not caſt out of himſelf, and his polluted generation of hirelings? Sure I am that he, and many others of them, have within theſe twelve months paſt, been frequent practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners of that which <hi>they</hi> call faſting and prayer; and are they not out of their own mouthes condemned for notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hypocrites, in what they did, ſince ſo many monſtrous <hi>evils</hi> and raging <hi>Devils,</hi> are yet remaining <hi>uncaſt</hi> out from among them? If they had been ſincere in their prayers and faſtings, could thoſe things which ſhould by them neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have been <hi>caſt out,</hi> be left ſtill <hi>ſtanding,</hi> and <hi>predominate.</hi> But Reader, I would further demand of <hi>William Thomas</hi> whether he will honeſtly ſtand to what he hath here aſſerted, without evaſion or recanting? if he will, then I muſt needs let him know, that he doth here preach, what in his book he doth moſt furiouſly condemn, <hi>viz. perfection</hi> in this life, for where there is no <hi>evil</hi> nor <hi>devil,</hi> left uncaſt out, there is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute <hi>perfection:</hi> He that is quit of all <hi>evil</hi> may confidently be proclaimed clean and perfect. Thus doth the burning blind zeal of guilty hearts, make men ſay, and unſay; aſſert a thing, and contradict it; bring forth a haſty birth, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it with their own hands.</p>
            <p>I could here give the Reader at large to underſtand (in many particular caſes) what uſe theſe men make of their prayers,<note place="margin">Faſting and prayer made a cloak for ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</note> and mock-faſts, <hi>viz,</hi> not to caſt out, but to cover o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>evils</hi> and <hi>devils,</hi> leſt they ſhould be too clearly diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. I could tell him (of which I preſume he is not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant) where miſcheivous deſigns have privately been carried on by his brethren (it's well if his hands were clear) under the ſpecious and pious vail of <hi>faſting</hi> and <hi>prayer;</hi> and I do confidently beleeve, that more miſchief hath bin hatch'd and brought forth, by that generation of men, under their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended religious covering of faſting and prayer, theſe fourteen years paſt, then can be parallell'd by many by paſt ages. I ſhould not envy, but honor them, would they once ceaſe to <hi>faſt for ſtrife</hi> and <hi>debate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 58.4.</note> and <hi>to ſmite with the fiſt of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:168420:12"/>(as at this day they do) and come to uſe that faſt which the <hi>Lord hath choſen,</hi> viz. <hi>To looſe the bands of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs,<note place="margin">Verſ. 6, 7.</note> to undo the heavy burdens, and to let the oppreſſed go free, and break every yoak,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Thomas</hi> concludeth his Epiſtle with a ſupplication, That the Lord would <hi>give a bleſſing to what he hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> The Devilliſh intentions, and attempts, of <hi>Balaam</hi> (that covetous hireling) to <hi>curſe</hi> innocent <hi>Iſrael,</hi> muſt be covered over with the religious vail of a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> with the oblation of <hi>Bullocks</hi> and <hi>Rams;</hi> and <hi>Balack</hi> was not without hope, but that God might give a bleſſing to ſuch pretended religious enterprizes,<note place="margin">Num. 22.40. and the 23.1. Verſ. 27.</note> for the obtaining of a cauſeleſs <hi>curſe</hi> upon that beloved people. But they ſhall miſs of their aims; for <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be <hi>bleſſed.</hi> Can <hi>William Thomas</hi> ask (with any hope to obtain) a <hi>bleſſing</hi> upon all the falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, ſlanders, and bitter words, with which he hath beſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the <hi>innocent</hi> in the day of his rage? Let him not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive himſelf in thinking, that, although he and his brethren in iniquity in <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> have appointed their ſeveral Mock-faſts, ſometimes in this Pariſh and ſometimes in that (as that hypocritical Soothſayer did the places for his ſacrifices) therefore the people of their anger muſt preſently be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed. For they that abide in the fear of the Lord, ſhall be ſure of a <hi>bleſſing;</hi> yea, they ſhall be <hi>altogether</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>And now that <hi>Willam Thomas</hi> hath in ſo large an Epiſtle, to his <hi>Friends and Neighbours, in and about the City of</hi> Briſtol, uttered ſo many words, without either <hi>Sobriety</hi> or <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> I ſhall alſo dip my pen in my <hi>tears,</hi> and in a few words unburden my oppreſſed ſpirit, to my fellow Citizens within that populous City.</p>
            <p>Oh that my <hi>head were waters, and mine eyes a fountain of tears, that I might weep day and night,</hi> for all your unlovely <hi>ſtruglings,</hi> and <hi>ſtrivings</hi> againſt your maker.<note place="margin">To the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
               </note> The Lord is my witneſs that my <hi>heart is pained,</hi> and my bowel; are even turned within me, whilſt I do ſadly behold your ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings from the way of your own peace. Your blind Leaders
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168420:13"/>have cauſed you to err, by drawing your minds from your true Leader. My hearts deſire and prayer, to the Lord for you all, is, that (returning) you might be <hi>ſaved,</hi> and being awakened to behold the Lord of life, whom you have igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly <hi>pierced</hi> and <hi>crucified,</hi> you may come to <hi>mourn for him, as one mourneth for his onely Son, and be in bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for him, as one that is in bitterneſs for his first born.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, I ſhall ſpeak a few words to you that are Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIRS,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Your temptations are many, your ſtanding ſlippery, your ſouls are precious, your days but few, your accompt great, your Judge righteous,<note place="margin">To the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
                     </note> and having once ſet foot within the gates of <hi>eternity,</hi> there is no place left either for repentance, or return.</p>
                  <p>Come therefore let us reaſon together, and, Oh, that I might prove an effectual Remembrancer, for the advantage of your immortal ſouls, before you <hi>go hence, and be no more ſeen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Conſider, that the ſword is not put into your hands to wound, but to guard tender conſciences. You are Uſurpers upon Chriſts prerogative, not Magiſtrates, whilſt you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to be Judges there, where he ſitteth as ſole <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>Law-giver.</hi> And the blood you draw thence will have an ill ſavour in his noſtrils, in the day that he ſhall enter into judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with you.</item>
                     <item>2. Be not hurried on by the fierce out-crys of your cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous <hi>Pulpits,</hi> to the execution of your own, or others wills and luſts upon the innocent; but be ye executioners of the <hi>righteous</hi> law upon the <hi>evil-doer.</hi> So ſhall you indeed give demonſtration that you <hi>bear the ſword for the Lord,</hi> by being a terror to the tranſgreſſor, but a <hi>praiſe to them that do well.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. Do not raſhly draw out your ſword againſt thoſe harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ones, whom your bloody Teachers (having nought wherewith they might juſtly ſtain their <hi>holy converſations</hi>)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168420:13"/>do cloath and repreſent to you, in the ugly garb of <hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers</hi> and <hi>Deceivers.</hi> Remember (oh remember ſo as to learn) that the <hi>Son</hi> of God, who ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> was not crucified by the ſtrict, outwardly religious, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, profeſſing, <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> as an <hi>innocent,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">☜</note> or a <hi>juſt</hi> man, but as a BLASPHEMER and a DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CEIVER.</item>
                     <item>4. Be not prevailed with to <hi>releaſe Barrabas,</hi> and give over <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be <hi>crucified,</hi> to gratifie the murderous appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, either of your prieſts or the multitude; conſidering, that although you may (with <hi>Pilat</hi>) <hi>waſh your hands,</hi> and (to thoſe eies that are dazled with fury, and prejudice, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt innocent <hi>Jeſus</hi>) appear clear from his <hi>blood,</hi> yet before the pure eyes of the Lord, will the condemning ſtain there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be found upon you ſo freſh, that you will by no means be thence cleanſed, but by the <hi>ſame</hi> blood, which you ſo cruelly ſhed.</item>
                     <item>5. Conſider that naked muſt you one day ſtand before the Lord (who is righteous in judgment) to render an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all your <hi>deeds done in the fleſh, whether they be good, or whether they be evil.</hi> And then no plea will find acceptance, but innocency; nor will any covering ſhelter you from the <hi>wrath</hi> of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> but holineſs. When the cry of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, which have been by you perſecuted, and impriſoned, ſhall come up before the Lord, little will it then avail you, to offer this for your Apology, <hi>viz.</hi> That you were told by your Teachers, that you ought to puniſh <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and that you ſhould <hi>do God ſervice, in killing</hi> them whom they repreſented to you as <hi>Deceivers.</hi> Out of his own mouth will Prieſt-ridden <hi>Pilat</hi> be then condemned, who was not onely fore-warned, that he ſhould have <hi>nothing to do with that juſt man;</hi> but alſo had a witneſs for Chriſt in his own <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;</hi> That he had committed nothing <hi>worthy either of bonds or of death.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>A few words more to all,<note place="margin">To the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol</hi> in general.</note> as well people as Magiſtrates within that great City, and I ſhall cloſe this.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In the <hi>fear</hi> of the Lord live, and abide. And to that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168420:14"/>of God in all your <hi>conſciences</hi> take heed, which is your day and night-companion; which followeth you to your Beds, your Tables, your Fields, your Shops, your Cloſets, your Counting-houſes; (and will alſo to your <hi>Death-beds</hi> and your <hi>Graves;</hi>) ſecretly checking you for thoſe miſcarriages, to which no eye is privy but the Lords, which doth often ſmite you when in your dealing, you do either lie, flatter, defraud, or over-reach your neighbour; I ſay to this, take heed, for it is the <hi>candle</hi> of the Lord to ſearch you; give ear to it when it convinceth you of ſin, and crieth to you for amendment; turn not your backs upon it, when it calleth upon you to repent ere it be too late, and to turn from <hi>lying vanities, to ſerve the living God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Reſign not up your precious ſouls, to the <hi>miſerable</hi> guidance of thoſe your. Teachers, who <hi>ſay and do not;</hi> that you ſhould condemn what they condemn, and approve what they approve. But be as wiſe for the eternal concernments of your ſouls, as you are for your outward man; ſee with your <hi>own</hi> eyes, hear with your <hi>own</hi> ears, and walk with your <hi>own</hi> feet. Paſs not away the few days of your pilgrimage, in liſtning to their ſtrong deluſions, ſuffering your ſelves to be lull'd aſleep, by thoſe pleaſing Dreamers even upon the brink of <hi>eternity.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. Awake, awake, ere the King of terrors ſeize upon you, and conſider whether you are able to ſtand in judgment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord at his coming. Suppoſe with your ſelves every hour, That that impartial executioner ſtood at your doors, ready to pull down your <hi>earthly Tabernacles,</hi> and ſtrip you naked of all this worlds glory (the <hi>husks</hi> on which you do now ſo contentedly feed) and ſeriouſly think, whether your foundation be <hi>ſure,</hi> and your building upon the <hi>Rock;</hi> that the violence of <hi>ſtorms,</hi> and <hi>winds</hi> you can abide, and not be <hi>removed.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. Remember, oh, remember, that through the gates of death muſt you paſs for your ſelves; and to the Lord muſt you render an account for your ſelves, and not another for you; Therefore lean not upon your blind guides (thoſe <hi>Egyptian reeds</hi>) whoſe pleaſing <hi>ſongs</hi> of periſhing glory
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168420:14"/>may ſatisfie your ſouls for a ſeaſon, but neither ſhall they die for you, nor give up your account for you, in the great and terrible day of the Lord. Let not their fury drive you, nor their perſwaſions allure you, to any thing, for which, the the witneſs of God in your own <hi>conſciences</hi> will condemn you. Do not at their inſtigation cry out for <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified;</hi> But firſt ask, <hi>what evil hath he done?</hi> neither be ye haſty (at their requeſt) to take the <hi>blood</hi> of thoſe upon your <hi>ſelves,</hi> and your <hi>children,</hi> whom they do decree as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemers,</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> had as high an eſteem of their Leaders (the Scribes, Phariſees, and High-prieſt) for wiſdom and godlineſs, as you can have of yours; and yet the blood of Chriſt, which they ſo confidently begged might be put upon their ſcore (being condemned for a BLASPHEMER) hath proved a grievous burden, under which their poſterities backs have bowed, for theſe Sixteen hundred years paſt.</item>
               <item>5. Stumble not at the meaneſs of Chriſts coming, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not attended with worldly <hi>pomp</hi> and glory. The <hi>Jews</hi> of old did ſplit themſelves againſt this rock. They expected their Meſſiah to be ſome outwardly illuſtrious <hi>Potentate;</hi> that ſhould be admired for his <hi>earthly</hi> greatneſs and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, that ſhould rather advance, then decry the glory of their <hi>Temple,</hi> their <hi>Worſhips,</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices, &amp;c.</hi> But when they ſaw him come as <hi>a root out of a dry ground,</hi> having no higher diſcent (that they knew) then from <hi>Joſeph</hi> a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter, and <hi>Mary</hi> a mean woman his Wife, having for his followers, <hi>Fiſhermen</hi> and <hi>Publicans, &amp;c.</hi> they were offended at him, and ſaw no <hi>form</hi> nor <hi>comlineſs in him, wherefore they might deſire him.</hi> If you ask your Teachers at this day, where Chriſt is to be found? They will tell you among the <hi>wiſe</hi> and the <hi>learned,</hi> the <hi>Rulers</hi> and the <hi>great</hi> men. And where he is ſpiritually worſhipped? They will tell you in the populous conventions, and their gay <hi>Steeple-houſes,</hi> where it muſt be religion for poor hearts to ſir, and hear their railings, and contradictions, inſtead of Divine Oracles. But alas! how different are the waies and works of the great God, from the waies and works of vain man! He chuſeth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168420:15"/>not many <hi>wiſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.27.28</note> not many <hi>mighty,</hi> not many <hi>noble;</hi> but on the contrary the <hi>fooliſh,</hi> the <hi>weak,</hi> the baſe, the <hi>deſpiſed</hi> peeces of the Creation doth he chuſe to manifeſt himſelf in.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Therefore when your Teachers cry out unto you, <hi>Lo here</hi> is Chriſt, <hi>lo there, believe</hi> them not. He is <hi>near</hi> that ſaveth you. Look not for him in the <hi>Palace,</hi> he is perſecuted thence; in the <hi>Inn,</hi> there is no <hi>room</hi> for him; but in the <hi>Manger</hi> you may find him: The <hi>contrite heart</hi> is the place of his habitation, and the <hi>broken</hi> and <hi>humble</hi> ſpirit, are the <hi>throne</hi> of his glory.</p>
            <p>In truth of love to your precious ſouls, have I written theſe things to you; which howſoever you ſhall interpret, yet herein have I peace, that my conſcience have I faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcharged towards you, as in the preſence of the Lord. Oh that my fellow-Citizens of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> would in the cool of the day, ſit down and ſeriouſly conſider what I have ſaid; and the God of all grace and mercy grant to you all, that in this your day <hi>you may know the things that do belong to your peace, before they be hid from your eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall now paſs from the Two Epiſtles to the Two Books; principally applying my ſelf (as I have before ſaid) to you two <hi>Chriſtopher Fowler</hi> and <hi>Simon Ford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt,<note place="margin">The Preamble to <hi>C. Fow.</hi> and <hi>S. Ford</hi>'s book examined.</note> Of the Preamble to your book; Which is a mixture made up of the old <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> ſtuff, <hi>viz.</hi> falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, flattery, and groſs hypocriſie. The firſt you mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in charging me with the maintaining of <hi>abſurd paradoxes in Civility, and blaſphemous hereſies in Religion.</hi> Wheras I am content to appeal to any ſober reader, which ſhall read my Epiſtle, and your <hi>Anſwer,</hi> whether there be any ſuch thing to be found, under my hand in the firſt, or proved upon me by you in the later: But you ſay, <hi>So you dare call</hi> the Doctrine that I undertake to ſhelter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Admirable poof! <hi>Thomas Speed</hi> is indicted in the face of the Nation, for maintaining <hi>abſurd Paradoxes, and blaſphemous Hereſies;</hi> How is this proved? <hi>Ipſi dixerunt. Chriſtopher Fowler</hi> and <hi>Simon Ford, dare call</hi> his doctrines
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168420:15"/>ſo, therefore they are ſo. Rare ingenuity! Who can eſcape the ſentence of theſe mens lying lips? when as they are ſo braſen-fac'd as to avouch a man in print to be a <hi>Blaſphemer,</hi> a <hi>Seducer,</hi> and what not; and then offer this to their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for evidence, that they <hi>dare call</hi> him ſo. You have the impudence, that you <hi>dare</hi> go up in your Pulpits, and call <hi>darkneſs light,</hi> and <hi>light darkneſs; good evil,</hi> and <hi>evil good; truth error,</hi> and <hi>error truth,</hi> and muſt your hearers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take your aſſertions for demonſtrations; that the things are indeed ſuch, becauſe you dare call them ſo?</p>
            <p>You go on with an hypocritical inſinuation, telling me, how <hi>compaſſionate you are towards me in this ſad deluſion I am under.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> I might juſtly be concluded to be under a <hi>ſad deluſion</hi> indeed, ſhould I credit your pretences of <hi>compaſſion</hi> towards <hi>me.</hi> Can that black ſpirit of rage and violence, cruelty and blood, that ruleth in <hi>you</hi> extend pitty towards <hi>me,</hi> who do appear bearing publick teſtimony againſt it? Horrible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit! palpable hypocriſie! like to the Egyptian darkneſs that might be <hi>felt!</hi> I am as far from believing you, as you are from having a witneſs in your conſciences to the truth of what you pretend. Had you but opportunity, the world would ſoon ſee that your <hi>compaſſions</hi> are mercileſs, and your mercies cruel. And ſhould the Lord ever permit the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet (as a plague upon this Nation) by the help of the beaſt, to be re-mounted upon the Throne, I do then expect no other fruits of your compaſſion towards me, then ſuch as your Fathers, <hi>Bonner</hi> and <hi>Gardner,</hi> did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend towards honeſt <hi>Bradfords,</hi> at the ſtake in Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field.</p>
            <p>But you have a fained ground of your <hi>compaſſion,</hi> viz. <hi>The repute which I had (till of late daies) for ſoundneſs, and orthodoxy in doctrinals, and ſome kind of moderation beyond o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of my Brethren in ſeparation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Whilſt I dwell'd in ſilence, and did not remove the Prieſts covering, that ſo the people might come to behold their filth and nakedneſs, I was <hi>ſound and orthodox in doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals;</hi> but now that I am weary of forbearing, and neceſſity
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168420:16"/>is laid upon me to cry out againſt the abominations of that polluted generation, I am preſently become <hi>unſound</hi> and <hi>heterodox.</hi> Reader, obſerve, and look throughout the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thou ſhalt finde, that, let a man be of what practiſe or opinion he will, if he can but ſpeak well of the Prieſts, and contend for them as Chriſts Miniſters; they will court him and cry him up for an orthodox, and a ſound Chriſtian. And on the contrary, take a man that is in his converſation ſober, holy, and unblameable. that is not onely painted with the profeſſion, but doth ſhew forth the power of godlineſs; yet if he cannot ſtrike ſail to the luſts and corrupt fancies of the Prieſts, the pulpits ſhall preſently ring of him, as a man of corrupt principles, unſound, and dangerous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
            <p>You further tell me, that by your <hi>putting pen to paper in this quarrel, you do not intend to take the cudgels out of the hands of that reverend man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> Cudgels? an inſtrument that I never finde in the hands of any Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt throughout the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but a ſit weapon for the hand of a <hi>fooliſh Shepheard.</hi> It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh ſuch as are ſtrangers to the weapons of <hi>Paul's</hi> and <hi>Peter's</hi> warfare, to ſtrike with cudgels. This Synodical club is an unanſwerable argument to enforce belief, and ſubmiſſion, when truth fails. But how came <hi>William Thomas</hi> to be a <hi>Reverend man?</hi> Are you not aſhamed to court one another with falſe and <hi>flattering titles?</hi> He ſtileth you in the Epiſtle to his Reader, his <hi>Reverend Brethren;</hi> and you him, <hi>That reverend man.</hi> Is this the language of the Scripture? did <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Peter</hi> ever mention each other by the name of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend</hi> Brother <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>reverend</hi> Brother <hi>Peter?</hi> Ye ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and preſumptuous ones, who durſt aſſume that title to your ſelves which the Spirit of Truth in the <hi>holy</hi> Scripture, appropriateth to the Lord alone, ſaying by the mouth of <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 111.9.</note> 
               <hi>Holy and REVEREND is his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The greateſt part of the reſidue of your Preamble conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of a high Encomium of <hi>William Thomas</hi> his excellent <hi>Miniſterial Qualifications.</hi> To which I ſhall only ſay, That when you have ſaid all you can in commendations of him,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168420:16"/>and he of you, by your <hi>fruits</hi> will you ſtill be known, and by the ſame ſhall you be judged by the righteous God, who accepteth no mans perſon in judgement. You may pleaſe your ſelves for a ſeaſon in painting one another in the view of men with the uſurped Titles of <hi>Reverend Brethren,</hi> and <hi>Reverend Brother,</hi> but be not deceived (although men may yet) <hi>God will not be mocked;</hi> as you <hi>ſow,</hi> ſo ſhall you <hi>reap,</hi> and if the blood of the innocent be found upon your heads; and conſequently, you do appear to be brethren in iniquity, the wages of blood ſhall you receive from the hand of him that is the avenger thereof.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>1.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In your firſt Section you quarrel with me, becauſe I prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeaſonable word of advice out of <hi>Seneca,</hi> in the Title<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page of my book; ſeeking to eclipſe the worth of his grave counſel, by branding him with the odious names of <hi>Heathen</hi> and <hi>Pagan:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> To which I reply, That however it be among men, yet before the Lord; it's not the <hi>name,</hi> but the <hi>nature,</hi> that makes the diſtinction. He that is not <hi>born again</hi> and made partaker of the <hi>new nature,</hi> although he may be guilded o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with the name of <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> yet in the judgement of truth, he is but a <hi>Heathen.</hi> He that bringeth forth the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſh fruits of lying, ſlandering, envy, pride, covetouſneſs and the like, cover him over with the faireſt vail you can, he is ſtill really but a <hi>Pagan.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom 2, 26, 27</note> If <hi>Seneca's uncircumciſion kept the righteouſneſs of the Law, ſhall not his uncircumſion be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for circumciſion, and judge you</hi> and many hundreds called Chriſtians, <hi>who by the letter and circumciſion do tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs the Law?</hi> And further, let me ſay, that if <hi>Seneca</hi> dwelt in the enjoyment and <hi>poſſeſſion,</hi> as well as the <hi>profeſſion,</hi> of thoſe many excellent principles, that are reputed his, I would chuſe rather (in the great day of the Lord) to be <hi>Seneca,</hi> then to be (unleſs they repent) either <hi>Chriſtopher Fowler</hi> or <hi>Simon Ford.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:168420:17"/>
               <head>SECT. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In your ſecond Section you tell me that you <hi>ſuppoſe I will give you leave to be ſo ingenious as to leave the anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my Book to</hi> William Thomas <hi>his able pen:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> I wiſh you were once ſo ingenious as to leave your lying, and let your ſayings and doings agree together; who not onely here, but in the Fifty ſeventh Section of your Book, do ſay that you will <hi>wave</hi> the anſwering of my <hi>Book</hi> becauſe you are <hi>advertiſed that</hi> William Thomas <hi>intendeth to take that task in hand himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. And yet (contrary to your ſeveral ſayings) you have undertaken the diſpute with me, touching many of the moſt ſubſtantial things contained in my Book, as the Reader may at large ſee by peruſing yours and mine.</p>
               <p>You proceed in the ſame Section, <hi>to con me thanks for the charitable advice I begin my</hi> Epiſtle <hi>withal,</hi> promiſing with a great many Lamb. like words <hi>to take warning,</hi> &amp;c. Inſtead of which <hi>William Thomas</hi> doth moſt bitterly revile me, calling me <hi>Falſe witneſs, Novice, one that do caſt reproach upon Gods ſervants,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> It was not without cauſe that <hi>William Thomas</hi> told his Reader in his Epiſtle to his Pamphlet, that his and (yours) his <hi>Brethrens meditations</hi> were <hi>ſo directed</hi> that you ſhould <hi>walk in ſomething a different way in one and the ſame work, and yet without difference.</hi> For in your ſeeming diſagreement you agree. <hi>You</hi> ſmite more in the dark, <hi>he</hi> more openly, in your work you <hi>agree,</hi> which is to ſupport your tottering <hi>Babel,</hi> one Maſter do you ſerve, and you ſhall receive your wages. In your way of proſecution you differ, juſt as much as a <hi>wolf in ſheeps cloathing,</hi> from the ſame creature in his proper ſhape.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>4.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>You begin your Fourth Section with a Query. <hi>Whether I do beleeve in earneſt, that thoſe Prophets of whom</hi> Michah
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168420:17"/>
                  <hi>ſpeaks that teach for hire, and divine for money, or thoſe whom Chriſt notes for doing their works to be ſeen of men,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are characters ſuiting the men of my indignation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwer. That I retain <hi>indignation</hi> againſt no man, looking upon every mans perſon as the workmanſhip of God; but againſt that evill ſpirit that ruleth and rageth in you and your brethren, do I bear a perfect <hi>indignation.</hi> And I do beleeve that to all <hi>Idol Shepheards</hi> in this Nation, that are acted by that ſpirit, do the <hi>Characters</hi> given both by <hi>Michah,</hi> and by Chriſt, moſt aptly <hi>ſuit,</hi> of which more in the next Section. And whereas you charge me with a deſire to reduce you <hi>to voluntary contributions.</hi> I ſay, if you are Chriſts Miniſters, why ſhould you not be contented with Chriſts maintenance? who that I can find in Scripture never ordained any other but this, <hi>freely ye have received,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 10.8.</note> 
                  <hi>freely give,</hi> and I never read of any of his in Scripture, that found their allowance too ſcant. But as for ſuch as you who do feaſt it, and brave it among the people, who muſt have for your <hi>luſts,</hi> as well as for your neceſſity, its no marvel if you refuſe a confinement within the limits of his mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>5.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your fifth Section beginnneth with a high-flown expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, demanding of me in the heigth of your ſpirits, <hi>who</hi> I am <hi>that do judge your hearts?</hi> Why? becauſe (ſay you) <hi>I tell you what you aim at, and ſet up as your end in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> That I did appeal to you in my Epiſtle whether you were not guilty of the ſame crime (of <hi>teaching for hire</hi>) with <hi>Micha's hirelings,</hi> is true. But it ſeemeth your own <hi>guilt</hi> made the application. Neither had I judged your hearts, but your works, if I had been poſitive in my charge againſt you. May not a common drunkard (with as much ſtrength of reaſon as you, interrogate me) demand of you, when you call him by his name, who are you that do <hi>judge</hi> his <hi>heart?</hi> Do not his fruits manifeſt what ſort of tree he is? If you
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168420:18"/>are not indeed ſuch as do preach for <hi>hire,</hi> and divine for <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tyth-exacters proved to teach for hire.</note> tell me, why is it that when you firſt begin to ſet up that trade, you do ſo earneſtly covet to get into that place which yeeldeth the largeſt <hi>maintenance,</hi> moſt Tythes, moſt acres of Gleab Land, or the greateſt augmentation? And when you are ſetled, why is it that you are ſo eaſily removed thence to a <hi>richer</hi> Benefice? Moreover, I have ſeen many ſore contentions among you Teachers, who ſhould get into a Pariſh endowed with a large Revenue; but how is it that you never contend, who ſhould come among a people, from whom there might be expected <hi>little</hi> money, and ſmal maintenance? In brief, do you not ſettle and remove juſt as Tenants do (for outward advantage) from a hard to a better bargain? And is it <hi>judging your hearts</hi> to ask, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch men as theſe <hi>do not teach for hire,</hi> and <hi>divine for money?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Thomas</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Page 5.</note> that he and his Brethren do take that which <hi>Chriſt ſaith they are worthy of.</hi> How is that proved?<note place="margin">Luk. 10.7.</note> by Chriſts words in <hi>Luke, The labourer is Worthy of his hire:</hi> whereas neither are they Chriſts <hi>Labourers</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe perſecutors) nor do they take his <hi>hire;</hi> for in the ſame verſe, Chriſt commandeth his labourers <hi>to eat and drink ſuch things</hi> as were <hi>given</hi> them; which way of maintenance they deſpiſe under the notion of <hi>voluntary contribution.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>6.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your Sixth Section ſmelleth ſo rank of loathſom hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, that it cannot but be abominable in the noſtrils of any ſober reader. Whilſt you pretend to <hi>adore that gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence which keepeth you out of the reach of my malice;</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe (ſtrange things would follow) you <hi>are aſſured you ſhould not be long Without perſecution,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> What pious and peaceable Martyrs, would you have your Reader to judge you two to be? who dare ſo devoutly <hi>adore that providence,</hi> who <hi>keepeth</hi> you from the <hi>reach</hi> of his <hi>malice,</hi> who never yet exchanged word with you, nor ſaw ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of your faces, nor had ought to do with you in his life
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168420:18"/>time, and who doth as much abominate that ſpirit that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuteth, as he doth the fouleſt devil that ever came out of the bottomleſs pit; Nay, who for this very thing ſake, principally doth deny you, and your outragious genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>But you ſay that you have already your <hi>ſhares in the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the tongues, and hands,</hi> of <hi>thoſe of</hi> my <hi>fellowſhip and communion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> To which I reply two things: Firſt, Whereas you do often throughout your Book, in ſcorn make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of me, and my <hi>Fraternity;</hi> me, and my <hi>Siſter-hood;</hi> me, and my <hi>Quaking generation;</hi> me, and my <hi>companions, &amp;c.</hi> I ſay, that I am of no ſect or faction, nor do I profeſs my ſelf of any other generation but of thoſe <hi>that fear God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 10 35.</note> 
                  <hi>and work righteouſneſs.</hi> And whatever name of reproach your venemous tongues do, for the truths ſake, caſt upon ſuch, I do eſteem it my honour to wear with them as my crown.</p>
               <p>Secondly, You mention three things that theſe perſecuters do to you. 1. <hi>Impoveriſh you and your families</hi> 2. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain your juſt and legal ſubſiſtance.</hi> 3. <hi>Diſturb you in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of your publick Worſhip.</hi> To the firſt, I ask, Is it truth, or is it a lye that you ſay? are you and your <hi>families</hi> indeed <hi>impoveriſhed,</hi> who do live high, fare deliciouſly, and vaunt it among men? Why ſirs, are you paſt all ſhame, that you can aver things ſo notoriouſly falſe? 2. Your ſecond is like unto this, for I hold <hi>communion</hi> and <hi>fellowſhip</hi> with none that do <hi>detain</hi> any mans <hi>juſt and legal ſubſiſtance:</hi> I do deny all ſuch injuſtice, and untill you ſhall particularly point out ſome of my communion that do act thus unjuſtly, you muſt ſtand for a couple of falſe accuſers. 3. The third piece of this your ſore perſecution is, the <hi>diſturbance</hi> you receive in your <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip:</hi> That is to ſay, when you have ſpent an hour, or more time in your Pulpits, in railing and raging, againſt ſuch as cannot bow down to the <hi>Image</hi> you have ſet up, ſome peaceable man or woman appeareth, crying out of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, or bidding the people repent, or the like; and what uſually followeth? why this, your ſheep (according to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168420:19"/>precepts and pattern of their Paſtors) fall foul on them, beat them, kick them, oftentimes draw their blood, drag them out of your Steeple-houſes, hurry them before Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and thence into ſome naſty Priſon or Dungeon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Rogues and Fellons, where they lie ſome two, ſome three, ſome four or more moneths; many of whom have by the unheard of tyranny of mercileſs Jailors, been brought to ſeal their teſtimony for Jeſus with their lives, and ſo faln aſleep. Now let all that are not intoxicated with the cup of rage, received from the hands of their Prieſts judge, who are the diſturbers, and who the perſecutors:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Thomas</hi> urgeth my own words againſt me, becauſe I asked in my Epiſtle,<note place="margin">Pag. 7.</note> whether <hi>the Biſhops did not in their days impriſon, and evil intreat many of them?</hi> And then ignorantly demandeth, why I ſhould ask them, <hi>Are you im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> The more is their ſhame, and the greater their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, that, having ſo lately gotten their necks from under the Biſhops yoaks, they ſhould now juſtifie the ſaid Biſhops in what they did to them, by laying <hi>Iron</hi> yoaks upon the necks of others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>7.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>You begin your ſeventh Section with boaſting. 1. That many of you live upon a <hi>free contribution maintenance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> What confuſion do the inhabitants of <hi>Babylon</hi> live in! But even now, in the cloſe of your fourth Section, you did tartly reflect on me, as one endeavouring to <hi>reduce you to voluntary contributions;</hi> as that which would ſoon <hi>reduce</hi> you to contempt; and yet here you glory in the ſame thing. So induſtrious is the Serpent to ſave his head, that he will gladly betake himſelf to any ſhelter. One while being afraid that the Maſter whom you ſerve will not ſupply your wants by <hi>voluntary contributions,</hi> you decry them, and deſpiſe them; and yet preſently after, to ſave your ſelves from being bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the name of <hi>Exactors,</hi> you aſſert them as the way of your maintenance, and glory in them. 2. You boaſt what
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168420:19"/>noble voluntiers many of you are in the work of your Maſter, by your maintaining many <hi>Lectures,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lectures made a covering.</note> Were it not for fear of being burthenſom to the Reader, I could tell him at large what trade theſe men do drive with moſt of thoſe things called <hi>Lectures.</hi> If the Prieſts have any wretched deſign to promote in the Country, then a Lecture muſt preſently be erected, in the the moſt publick and convenient place for their convening, that under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of that they may <hi>joyntly</hi> confer about, and contrive, the effecting of that miſchief which they had before <hi>ſingly</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected. But are you two of the number of theſe Voluntiers? how cometh it then to paſs,<note place="margin">Simon Ford.</note> that one of you did ſome time ſince erect a Lecture in the Town of <hi>Reading,</hi> and finding your free <hi>Contribution maintenance,</hi> coming in but ſlowly thence, did ſoon let the Lecture fall? Whatever you proclaim of your ſelves, to thoſe that know you not, yet the people of the Town of <hi>Reading</hi> do well know, that you live by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother rule then you pretend to <hi>(viz.)</hi> no penny, no <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noſter!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But though ſome of you are thus free of your labour, yet others you confeſs do preach by <hi>Indentures.</hi> For which their practice, I did in my Epiſtle demand <hi>a rule in Scripture.</hi> And you, to ſave them from condemnation, do offer an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittance under <hi>Pauls</hi> hand, who ſaith, that <hi>he that doth not provide for his own is worſe then an Infidel,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.8.</note> and hath denied the faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> And is this your rule by which you indent for your wages, before you dare enter upon your work? What a ſhameful begging of the queſtion is this? Do you two pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend your ſelves to be ſuch great Maſters of learning, and eminent Zealots in Religion, and yet reaſon like men at once bereft of all honeſty and underſtanding? Becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> proclaimeth him that doth not <hi>provide</hi> for himſelf, and <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily</hi> to <hi>be worſe then an Infidel,</hi> doth he thereby juſtifie any means (right or wrong) by which a man may make proviſion, as lawful and commendable? tell me by this wild Logick, how you will be able to convince a common Thief that he doth evil? Suppoſe a poor man ſhould come and ſteal a buſhel of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168420:20"/>corn out of either of your Barns, or a bag of money out of your Cheſts, for the ſupply of the neceſſities of <hi>himſelf</hi> and <hi>his;</hi> if you accuſe him for an evil doer, may he not offer your own rule in evidence for himſelf, and reaſon thus; He that maketh <hi>proviſion for himſelf and family,</hi> proveth himſelf not <hi>worſe then an Infidel;</hi> But I (may he ſay) by ſtealing do make <hi>proviſion</hi> for my <hi>ſelf</hi> and <hi>family, Ergo, &amp;c.</hi> Nay further will not the moſt notorious thief upon <hi>Salisbury</hi> Plain (who doth rob for neceſſity) find patronage for his wickedneſs under ſuch Tutors as you are? Ask him whilſt he is taking a purſe from a Traveller by what rule he doth act ſuch injuſtice? By the ſame rule may he ſay as the Prieſts act by, when they <hi>indent</hi> for their hire, <hi>viz.</hi> that I might make <hi>proviſion</hi> for my <hi>ſelf</hi> and <hi>family,</hi> and ſo not ſhew my ſelf <hi>Worſe then an Infidel,</hi> and <hi>a denier of the faith.</hi> Now Sirs, reflect upon your ſelves ſeriouſly, and ſee your co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering pull'd off you, and to that of God in both your conſciences do I appeal, whether ever any age of the world afforded Sophiſters, that did more palpably abuſe the holy Scriptures to patronize their own luſts, then you, and the reſt that call themſelves Miniſters do at this day.</p>
               <p>You proceed in the ſame Section to tell me of ſome of mine, <hi>Who Wander up and down to the manifeſt and apparent ruine of themſelves, and thoſe that they are bound to provide for.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Such wanderers are none of <hi>mine</hi> (for I deny them) but ſome of yours.<note place="margin">Si accuſaſſe ſat ſit, quis innocens erit?</note> Did ever any man or woman, whom you in ſoorn call Quakers, beg relief of either of you? or can you quote one of their families that is thus ruined? I can produce you inſtances enough of Pariſh Prieſts, who have drunk and rioted themſelves and families into poverty; by which character I am ſure one may find many <hi>Infidels</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your generation, who yet talk much of faith. But who can eſcape the ſtroak of your ſlanderous pens, who <hi>dare</hi> preach any thing, print any thing, and produce no other proof for what you avouch, but this, that you <hi>dare ſay</hi> it is ſo? Nay, to what height of impudence are you come who
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:168420:20"/>
                  <hi>dare</hi> belie the Son of God, in ſaying preſently after, that he commanded his to <hi>travel about to declare without ſhooes on their feet.</hi> Monſtrons impiety!<note place="margin">Mar. 10.8, 9, 10</note> what is it not enough for you to heap ſlanders, falſhoods, and reproaches upon me, but you muſt attempt to faſten an untruth upon him, who is truth it ſelf? Read that Scripture again, and then ſee if you can be ſo wicked as to ſay, that Chriſt commandeth that which never proceeded out of his lips, <hi>viz.</hi> that his ſhould <hi>travel without ſhooes upon their feet.</hi> Reader, what horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fables would theſe men faſten on the Scripture among the ignorant, were they kept ſealed in Greek or Latin? when as they dare even now to aſſert ſuch things to be in them, for aſſerting which, the meaneſt child that can read Engliſh, may prove them Liars?</p>
               <p>Much ado you keep in this Section labouring in confuſion, and all to prove that which I never denied,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.6. to 14.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> that they that <hi>preach the Goſpel</hi> ſhould <hi>live of the Goſpel.</hi> Which Scripture, you ſay, the <hi>adverſaries to Miniſters maintenance do paſs over in deep ſilence;</hi> and you <hi>expect</hi> it will be <hi>by me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,</hi> &amp;c. To which I ſay; that I do ſubſcribe to the truth of what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith all along in that Chapter, <hi>viz.</hi> That he that <hi>planteth a vineyard</hi> ought to <hi>eat of the fruit thereof;</hi> and he that <hi>feedeth a flock, ought to eat of the milk thereof,</hi> &amp;c. But what is all this to you? who are not <hi>Planters,</hi> but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoyers; not <hi>Feeders,</hi> but devourers of the flock? or if you were ſuch, what rule is this for your vexatious ſuits at law for your maintenance? Doth the Scripture ſay that <hi>Paul</hi> took thoſe men by the <hi>throats,</hi> that gave him not the tenth of all their increaſe? when you ſhall come to do <hi>Pauls</hi> work, and tread in <hi>Pauls</hi> footſteps, I ſhall not deny you <hi>Pauls</hi> wages.</p>
               <p>You cloſe this Section with as notable a falſhood as the reſt, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>no man holds the nine parts by firmer law in theſe Nations, then the Miniſter claims his tenth by.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> If a man purchaſe ten acres of Land by meaſure, and payeth a full conſideration for each foot of the ſaid ten acres, have you as much right to the tenth acre, who never advanced peny towards the purchaſe, as he hath to the other
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:168420:21"/>nine, who paid the full value for the whole? If a poor man having a great family to maintain, do rent five acres of land, and after he hath plowed it, and ſowed it, and he, and his, have lived in hope (perhaps with <hi>naked</hi> backs, and <hi>empty</hi> bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies) to receive the fruits of all their labor and toil; have you as good <hi>right</hi> to the tenth ſheaf, as the poor oppreſſed man hath to the other nine? Well you may have a law that will own you in ſuch your cruelties in the Courts of men; but ſure I am, you have no law that will juſtifie you in the preſence of the Lord, and that ſhall you ſurely one day wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to your ſhame and ſorrow, without repentance.</p>
               <p>Where as I demanded (in my Epiſtle) a rule in Scripture, <hi>by which the teachers of the Nation did exact the tenth of their encreaſe, who did not hear them, nor own them for their Paſtors?</hi> William Thomas anſwereth me by another Query, <hi>viz. Muſt a Miniſter be deprived of the members of his Church, and the maintenance of his place, both at once?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Is this Query a rule in Scripture to juſtifie their practice! Reader, thou that art ſober, judge, whether this be an anſwer beſpeaking him that gave it forth, to be a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of reaſon, muchleſs of the Goſpel. Theſe are the men that do ſo paſſionately aſſert the Scripture to be their rule in words, and yet being demanded a rule thence for their practice, in a matter of ſuch moment, are ſo ſhameleſs as to offer a ſenceleſs Query inſtead of Scripture. And thou maiſt further obſerve; that throughout both their books they have not produced any one Scripture, that do prove their practice in the things they are accuſed of. But inſtead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of do offer the conceptions of their own brains, or elſe ſuch meanings and ſences as they pleaſe to force upon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; which if a man refuſe to accept of, he is preſently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for an <hi>Antiſcripturiſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>8.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In your eighth Section, both you and <hi>William Thomas</hi> do confeſs the matter of fact, <hi>viz.</hi> That many of your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are <hi>found wallowing in the common mire,</hi> &amp;c: And you
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:168420:21"/>ſay alſo, that you do bewaile it. Which I ſhould have ſome reaſon to beleeve alſo, were your Pulpits fill'd with as frequent declamations, againſt the abominations of ſuch your pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted Brethren, as they are with <hi>invectives</hi> againſt thoſe, that ſtand up to bear witneſs againſt theirs and your wickedneſs. In the cloſe of this Section, you ſpeak of <hi>Swearing, drunken, and otherwiſe diſorderly companions, that frequent the Quakers aſſemblies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> To which I ſay, That I have been often in the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of thoſe peaceable people (and do bleſs the Lord that I lived to be in them) where I have ſeen many <hi>drunken, ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, diſorderly companions:</hi> But they were not <hi>of</hi> them with whom they aſſembled, though they were <hi>among</hi> them; but the ſcabby ſheep that belonged to ſome <hi>Prieſt</hi> or other, that came there to act the ſame part in thoſe Aſſemblies, that their Shepheards do in the pulpits <hi>(viz)</hi> ſcoff, ſcorn, reproach, and revile the innocent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>9.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your ninth Section is full of venome and bitterneſs, of taunts and unſavory ſcoffs; which (as I ſaid in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) I ſhall let fall into the Channel. You accuſe me for calling the Scriptures <hi>in ſcorn your rule;</hi> For which I can boldly, and truly charge you to be a couple of malicious ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars. For the Scriptures of truth, I do highly eſteem, and do bleſs the Lord for them; neither have I, through all my Epiſtle or Book, mentioned them with that apparent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt that you do, calling them in your Tenth Section; <hi>your low Rule,</hi> and Section Sixty two, <hi>your old Rule.</hi> When my pen doth drop ſuch contemptible expreſſions touching the Scriptures as theſe are, then write me down among the number of thoſe that do <hi>ſcorn</hi> it with your ſelves. Until then know, that the Scriptures I do own againſt you, and your prating companions, that do pretend to cry up the Scriptures in word onely, ſerving your luſts upon them, making a trade to talk of them thereby to get a livelihood; but do moſt wretchedly abuſe them and trample them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:168420:22"/>feet by contradicting them in your practices.</p>
               <p>After this, having expoſtulated with you, touching all your violence, and perſecution, againſt Chriſt in his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, minding you of the judgement of the great Day; you return this in anſwer, <hi>viz Judge not that you be not judged.</hi> Juſt as if a man ſhould come to an unclean perſon that ſquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth away his precious hours, in the filth and open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs of the world, and deal with him for his iniquities, and he ſhould return this in anſwer, <hi>Judge not that ye be not judged.</hi> The <hi>innecent</hi> do not dread judgement, but you that are guilty of all the violence and cruelty, mentioned in that Epiſtle, to judgement muſt you come, and that before that God who will not accept of a ſcoff, or an impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, for an anſwer to what ſhall then be demanded of you. That which <hi>William Thomas</hi> ſaith in this particular, hath ſo little weight in it, that I ſhall not ſpend time or paper to make a recital of it, muchleſs judge it worthy of an anſwer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>10.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>You need not have told me in your Tenth Section of your readineſs to perſecute,<note place="margin">Prieſts wait for commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute.</note> worry, and impriſon others, were you but <hi>legally commiſſioned thereunto.</hi> We very well know you would ſoon be upon <hi>Pauls</hi> work, could you but once gain his <hi>Letters.</hi> Your Brethren in the beginning of Queen <hi>Maries</hi> reign were very thirſty after blood, but could not drink their fill, until by the Seſſion of a Parliament, they were <hi>legally commiſſioned</hi> to draw it. And ſhould this, or any ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Parliament, put the cup into the Prieſts hands, and bid them draw, I do confidently beleeve (that as far as in them lies) there ſhould not be a drop of blood left, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the veins of any true <hi>Iſraelite</hi> in the Nation. Neither will that plea juſtifie you (when you ſhall be arraigned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lamb ſitting upon the Throne) to ſay, that you have perſecuted and worried none but <hi>diſguiſed Wolves.</hi> For they that are the Lambs followers never perſecuted any; neither do the Scriptures or any other Hiſtories, repreſent
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:168420:22"/>them to us in the poſture of impoſers, or afflictors, but of <hi>Bearers</hi> and <hi>Sufferers.</hi> Beſides, is not every man a Wolf in your eſteem, who cannot bow the knee to <hi>Baal?</hi> and is it not the greateſt crime of thoſe, whoſe blood you ſo long to be dabling in; that they are innocent? yea, I bear teſtimony to it, that he that at this day <hi>departeth from iniquity, maketh himſelf a prey</hi> to the cruel teeth of the <hi>falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this <hi>William Thomas</hi> addeth his mite, to help you at a dead lift as well as he can. He confeſſeth that the <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament was called upon by the Presbiters, for the ſetling of a government,</hi> &amp;c. That is, that every pragmatical <hi>Pariſh-Prieſt</hi> might have been a Biſhop, and the decrees of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous Synod, might have been as the giving forth of the <hi>Law</hi> from <hi>mount Sinai</hi> by the mouth of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to which whoſoever would not yield obedience, might be <hi>cut</hi> off without mercy. Next he would inſinuate the <hi>badneſs</hi> of the people called Quakers, and the ſadneſs of their <hi>condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> becauſe of the many <hi>wiſe,</hi> and (as he calleth them) <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men,</hi> that cannot <hi>approve, nor favour them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Hath this man never read the Scripture? Or hath he forgotten how the <hi>wiſe, religious, devout Jews</hi> (both men and women) did with one lip cry out for Jeſus to be <hi>crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi> and was that an argument he was a <hi>bad</hi> man?</p>
               <p>And laſtly, he ſuggeſteth grave ground of ſuſpition, that they that have an <hi>evill eye upon the Miniſters, will not be long from overthrowing Magiſtracy:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> How cloſe this poor heart doth cling to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, whilſt he will be his vaſſall, and his footſtool? Here is the old Court Doctrine, no Biſhop, no King. And as to <hi>the fifth Monarchy</hi> he ſpeaketh of, I ſay, that I own, or expect none but this, that Chriſt may rule and reign, as King in the hearts of men; and then I am ſure the <hi>beaſt</hi> and the <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> muſt both to the <hi>bottomleſs pit,</hi> whence they came.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:168420:23"/>
               <head>SECT. <hi>11.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your next Section is onely a Preparatory to what you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſay in thoſe that follow; and accordingly I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to it. You tell me, that you <hi>dare not let</hi> me <hi>alone to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen the world into a good eſteem of my opinions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> I know the man of ſin, whoſe cauſe ye negotiate, is very vigilant to preſerve his tottering kingdom, ſo that if truth hath but its current, it will ſoon ſhake the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations thereof. And therefore it is, that he doth ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtir himſelf in you, and others of his inſtruments, to ſupport that, which would be the joy of thouſands of the Lambs followers to ſee razed to the ground.<note place="margin">Page 12.</note> 
                  <hi>William Thomas</hi> telleth his Reader, that I drew up the following <hi>charge in jeſt.</hi> But this muſt be reckoned among the reſt of his pittifull miſtakes; for I drew it up in earneſt; and becauſe yet I have not, now I ſhall acquaint the Reader with the ground of my drawing it up, <hi>viz</hi> Hearing a great noiſe and cry in the Nation, Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits on fire, Cities on fire, and many ſeparated Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on ſire, and all becauſe of the coming forth of a people in ſcorn called <hi>Quakers;</hi> I began to make inquiſition into the riſe, and bottom of all this, and what was in the lives, manners, and declarations of the ſaid people, that gave occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to this ſo great an out-cry. And by inquiry I found, that the rage vented againſt them both from Preſs and Pulpits, had its occaſion from thoſe fifteen Particulars mentioned in my Epiſtle, which I thought meet to publiſh unto the world, that all men might ſee that it was not for theſt, murther, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, ſwearing, lying, grinding the faces of the poor, tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mens throats for their maintenance, plucking the bread from betwixt the teeth of the needy, nor for ſuing men at the Law, and throwing them into naſty priſons, for the tenth of all their encreaſe, that the teachers of this Nation were ſo cruelly outragious againſt theſe men; but for matters that concerned the worſhip of the Lord their God.</p>
               <p>Now whereas <hi>Chriſtopher Fowler</hi> and <hi>Simon Ford</hi> do ſay that I have not drawn up all they have to ſay againſt them,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:168420:23"/>(wherefore they ſo eagerly purſue their blood) but that they have <hi>matters of greater moment to exhibit againſt them;</hi> which they call <hi>[The Quakers Doctrines]</hi> in their 54<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Section I ſay, that laying aſide the notorious lies, and ſlanders, coucht in that Liſt; I doubt not before I have ended with them, to ſpread before the ſober Reader ſuch a true Catalogue of theirs and their brethrens Doctrines and Practiſes (which I will prove to their faces) that will make his heart aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and his eares to tingle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>12.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Section beginneth thus; <hi>You take it ill to be charged as blaſphemers for affirming that Chriſt is the light that enlightneth every one that cometh into the world</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep:</hi> Ill? Why is it well that you charge any man to be a blaſphemer for reciting a Text of Scripture? Are not you excellent Advocates for the Scripture, that would faſten the character of blaſphemer, upon a man for the bare quoting of it? nay you add, that <hi>I ſtand upon my purgation,</hi> For what? becauſe I made mention of two Scriptures in <hi>John?</hi> is this ſuch a crime that I need a purgation? Obſerve Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, notwithſtanding all theſe mens verbal zeal, what their boſom thoughts are of Scripture. But what would you have? you ſay, you <hi>hope I will give you leave to aske me a few queſtions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Why had you not ſpoke out what is within, and ſaid, what this <hi>Speed</hi> hath ſaid is plain Scripture, and therefore we dare not (for fear of the people) but ſay it is truth; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we will try, if we can, to catch him with our Queries, and meanings, that we may have ſome matter to work upon. But hold Sirs, do you uſe to bring men to their arraignment at the Bar, and then ask them if they know ought againſt <hi>themſelves</hi> whereof you may accuſe them? Let the Reader take notice of the ſubtilty of theſe men, that throughout my whole book, where they find my words ſo plain and true, that they have nought to anſwer, they (to cover over their own guilt) do either firſt go to making meanings on my words;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:168420:24"/>or ſecondly, fly from the matter in hand, and begin to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Queries, thereby to amuſe the Reader, and blunt the edge of his intention upon what hath been ſaid.<note place="margin">Pagei 5.</note> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is that <hi>William Thomas</hi> telleth his Reader in his Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth page, that his <hi>Brethren have dealt providently with me in querying me out of my ſtarting holes.</hi> That is to ſay, out of my plain Scripture into meanings. For when the truth of plain Scripture, which I quote, do ſo rub their fore, that they cannot bear it, then they fall to querying about ſenſes and meanings.</p>
               <p>You ask me firſt, <hi>What light that is, with which Chriſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteneth every man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Scripture beareth witneſs that the work of Chriſts Miniſters conſiſted in <hi>turning men from darkneſs to light,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 26.18.</note> and do you two pretend to have been Chriſts Miniſters for ſo many years paſt, and yet declare ſo much ignorance of your work, as now to ask <hi>what that light is?</hi> What is that converſion that your preaching have wrought upon your miſerable hearers, more then from one degree of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to another, who yet remain ſtrangers to that light to which they ſhould have been converted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Thomas</hi> maketh a great cry about the <hi>light,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>VVill. Thomas</hi> his confeſſion touching the light.</note> with his meanings, and interpretations, his ſuppoſitions and diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, calling (but not proving) it a <hi>natural light,</hi> and all to ſtifle it if he could: Although in the cloſe of his thirteenth page he is made to confeſs as much of it,<note place="margin">Page 13.</note> as ever I heard or read from the pens or lips of the men of his anger, <hi>viz. Chriſt lighteth every man that cometh into the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☞</note> 
                  <hi>though not by ſaving illumination, yet by ſaving revelation</hi> (a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction which I underſtand not, but he will explain it) <hi>that is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>by that Goſpel-revelation that is fit to ſave them, though divers receiving the revelation (do through their own fault) loſe the ſalvation.</hi> Let himſelf beware that having the reevlation he loſe not the ſalvation.</p>
               <p>And now leſt you ſhould think I am aſhamed to declare what I own touching this light of Chriſt, I ſhall briefly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs what I underſtand of it.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. This light of Jeſus is that in which all the deceit of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:168420:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>Prieſts is ſeen, and witneſſed againſt; and therefore it is that they do ſo bandy againſt it, ſpeaking all manner of evil of it, refuſing to come to it, <hi>becauſe their deeds are evil.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. This light is that which diſcovereth the temptation to evil before it is committed, and checketh and convinceth for ſin when it is commited.</item>
                  <item>3. It is that which followeth many a man, day by day throughout his life, ſmiting him for that hidden wickedneſs he liveth in, prompting him to return to his Maker, which he ſtubbornly reſiſting paſſeth his days with a galled conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his grave.</item>
                  <item>4. It is the ſame that was in <hi>Enoch, Noah, Abraham</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the ſame to which the <hi>Prophets, John Baptiſt,</hi> and the Apoſtles did bear witneſs: So that, wherever it is now, it leadeth not contradictory, but according to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the ſame <hi>holy men</hi> recorded in the Scriptures of truth.</item>
                  <item>5. Laſtly, It is that which will be the certain condemnation of all thoſe, who having it, obey it not,<note place="margin">Joh. 3.i9.</note> but <hi>love darkneſs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then light.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Here I would cloſe what I have to ſay to your anſwer to this firſt particular; but that <hi>William Thomas</hi> hath not yet done, being very wrath that I asked, <hi>What need of their teachings?</hi> And thereupon inſolently demandeth of me, <hi>What need had Chriſt to ſend forth his Apoſtles, and bid them go and teach all Nations?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. What the Apoſtles taught was from the <hi>living</hi> Spirit of Jeſus, and not from <hi>liveleſs</hi> traditions; neither were they fire-brands where they came, as he and his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are, teaching the people to perſecute, impriſon and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy one another, as they do; but manifeſted the way of peace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They taught men to turn from darkneſs unto light, but theſe men ask, <hi>what the light is? quarrelling, fighting,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 16.</note> 
                  <hi>raging</hi> againſt it. Nay as if he himſelf could not render it ſufficiently odious, he chargeth his Readers to <hi>have a jealous eye upon it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some Scriptures there are that do ſtand much in his way,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:168420:25"/>which I beleeve he heartily wiſheth were razed out of the Bible, and doth endeavor all he can to make them Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal, ſuch as theſe, <hi>They ſhall teach no more every man his neighbour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 31.34. 1 Joh 2 27.</note> &amp;c. And that in <hi>John, Ye need not that any man teach you,</hi> &amp;c. To which Scriptures (he ſaith) he will for the <hi>ſatisfaction of weaker Chriſtians ſpeak ſomething.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 17.</note> I wiſh he, and the reſt of the traders upon Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, would let the Scriptures abide pure as they are, and not hew them, and clip them, and curtail them as they do; and all to make them ſpeak according to their corrupt fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. They muſt be weak Chriſtians indeed, that muſt receive ſatisfaction from Scripture ſo <hi>rack'd</hi> and <hi>manacled</hi> as they are before they come out of his hands.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>13.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your thirteenth Section ſheweth your readineſs to wrangle with me about words, if you could find any matter to work upon. Something you muſt have to ſay to me (for form ſake) touching my <hi>ſecond Article.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 19.</note> Although <hi>William Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> doth ſo fully aſſent to what is ſaid therein, that he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately ſaith, that if I ſay the <hi>Teachers of this Nation do charge</hi> the people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> with <hi>the bare affirming</hi> thereof, it is <hi>an untruth.</hi> But if <hi>I mean</hi> ſo, or ſo, then he ſaith, it's an <hi>untruth</hi> alſo. So let me ſay or mean what I will, if they like it not I muſt be condemned. In the cloſe of this Section you come to ſpeak ſcoffingly of this light; of which take heed and beware, for a ſwift witneſs ſhall you find it to be againſt all your unrighteouſneſs (to your condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) in the great day of the Lord.</p>
               <p>You ſay you are little <hi>beholding to my principles, who would reduce you to the condition of Heathens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Well were it for a great part of you, that you were in the condition of thoſe <hi>Heathens,</hi> whoſe <hi>uncircumciſion do fulfill the Law,</hi> whilſt <hi>you,</hi> who bleſs your ſelves with the name of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2.27.</note> are <hi>found tranſgreſſors</hi> of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:168420:25"/>
               <head>SECT. <hi>14.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In your fourteenth Section you would be quarrelling with me if you durſt, and could you handſomly quit your ſelves; of thoſe Scriptures I quote about <hi>perfection,</hi> you would proclaim me a <hi>Blaſphemer.</hi> And if <hi>that be all I hold of perfection, yet thoſe of my perſwaſion</hi> (you ſay) <hi>are not ſo modeſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> If by thoſe of my perſwaſion, you intend the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple called <hi>Quakers,</hi> (whom ye ſeek to devour) I ſay, that I never found any of them, to preach, or profeſs, any other <hi>perfection,</hi> then ſuch as Chriſt exhorted to, and <hi>Paul</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Saints witneſſed. About which, you and <hi>William Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> do diſtinguiſh with all the art you can, to ſtop the mouth of the Scripture. But when you have done all, what <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſed therein, is ſtill <hi>wiſdom among them that are perfect.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.6.</note> And here again you are craving <hi>allowance</hi> to <hi>ask</hi> me <hi>a few queſtions.</hi> Becauſe you can finde no flaw in plain truth, you would therefore by queſtoning finde ſome if you could.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Thomas</hi> cloſeth his diſcourſe about <hi>perfection,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 21.</note> with a ſtrange ſaying, <hi>viz. our duty here is to be always perfecting,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.23.</note> 
                  <hi>but</hi> (our labour is in vain for) <hi>it belongeth to our wiſedom to know, that we can never be fully perfected till the last day, wherein our ſouls ſhall be among the ſouls of juſt men made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> What a thick miſt doth rage caſt before the eyes of the envious? Could one think that one that pretendeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to have been ſo long a Miniſter of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ. 22</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ΠΡΟΣΕ ΛΗΛΥ'ΘΑΤΕ.</hi> Sed ACCES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SISTIS. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Τ ΕΤΕ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ΛΕΙΩΜΕ'<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ΝΩΝ.</hi> Ad ſpiritus juſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FECTOR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M</note> ſhould lay down ſuch an aſſertion, and produce a Scripture for proof, ſpeaking point-blank contrary thereunto? <hi>We cannot be fully perfected</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>untill the laſt day</hi> How doth he prove it? Why, by the words of the Author to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who ſaith to the <hi>Hebrews, Ye ARE come to the spirits of the juſt men made perfect.</hi> Doth he ſay in the future tenſe, they <hi>ſhould</hi> come at the <hi>laſt</hi> day? or doth he ſay they are come to thoſe that <hi>ſhall</hi> be perfect? doth he not ſay in the preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect tenſe, they <hi>ARE</hi> already come, <hi>to the ſpirits of juſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:168420:26"/>men ALREADY made perfect?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 44.25.</note> is not the Scripture fulfilled at this day, which ſaith, <hi>The Lord maketh the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viners mad, and turneth the wiſe men backward, and maketh their knowledge fooliſh?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>15.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In your fifteenth Section you offer little, ſave a threat what a ſevere <hi>reckoning</hi> you will have with me hereafter: Againſt which, I doubt not but to appear ſo armed with <hi>truth,</hi> as to be able therewith to quench all the <hi>fiery darts,</hi> that you and your Maſter have ready in your Quivers to ſhoot at me.</p>
               <p>But <hi>William Thomas</hi> ſupplieth that wherein you are want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Page 23.</note> in paſſion and ignorance; exceeding zealous he is in this particular; for herein conſiſteth the life of the Prieſts <hi>trade,</hi> in <hi>mangling, tearing,</hi> and <hi>confounding</hi> the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> which they call Interpretations. The Scripture witneſſeth, that <hi>none knoweth the mind of God, ſave the Spirit of God, and he to whom the Spirit ſhall reveal it.</hi> Now obſerve, Ten men do ſend each of them a Son to the Univerſity, in order to their outward preferment, where having ſpent ſeven or more years, they are called home by them that ſent them, and by crouching,<note place="margin">It is the ſpirit not ſtudy in a Univerſity, that maketh able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> and cringing, and perhaps the help of ſome of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> his <hi>purchaſe money,</hi> a Benefice is gained for each of them. Now theſe men being <hi>Miniſters</hi> in <hi>William Thomas</hi>'s account, he aſſerteth it to be their <hi>imployment, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them of God, to be Meſſengers and Interpreters.</hi> As if they had gained the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and conſequently the <hi>mind of God,</hi> by the conſumption of a few years in a Univerſity. One of theſe readeth <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> another <hi>Jerom,</hi> a third <hi>Calvin,</hi> a fourth <hi>Luther, Peter Martyr,</hi> &amp;c. their interpretations of Scripture, and then they come forth to the people and ſay, this is the meaning, and t'other is the meaning: And is this to interpret by the Spirit? May not the worſt of men, who have not the Spirit but <hi>hate</hi> the Spirit, nay, may not the worſt of Devils, who well underſtand the languages in which thoſe Commentators writ, do the ſame?</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:168420:26"/>
               <p>Moreover take theſe ten young Divines, which he calleth <hi>Gods Meſſengers and Interpreters,</hi> and give them ten difficult places of Scripture a part each from other to interpret, and it may be there ſhall not five of them agree in one interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now mind, if theſe men have not the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> they are not fit <hi>Interpreters,</hi> becauſe they cannot know Gods <hi>mind,</hi> without that <hi>Spirit.</hi> If they have that Spirit,<note place="margin">The Spirit never contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicteth it ſelf</note> I demand, whether the ſame ſpirit interpreting in one man, do contradict it ſelf giving an interpretation in another? If there be but one Spirit of truth, and that ſpeaketh in every man (where it is) the ſame thing, then it's clear that theſe men whom he calleth <hi>Meſſengers</hi> and <hi>Interpreters,</hi> do bring forth the fancies and vain conceptions of their own brains (and not the mind of God by the Spirit of God) who do ſo jangle, and contradict one another in their interpretations. And therefore his charging it as a <hi>wicked error</hi> (in the ſame page) upon thoſe that deny their <hi>expoſitions,</hi> and interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, is but a Bug-bear to ſtartle the ignorant. I ſay to thee Reader, Abide faithful in the counſel of the Lord, and thou ſhalt know his mind. Live in that <hi>Spirit</hi> that gave forth the Scriptures, by the mouthes of <hi>holy men,</hi> and the Scripture will be plain unto thee, for it's that Spirit that unſealeth the myſtery. Thy ſoul is moſt precious, therefore let not the <hi>falſe Prophet</hi> deceive thee. As I have formerly told thee, ſo now I tell thee again, in bowels of love, thou muſt die for thy <hi>ſelf,</hi> and not thy <hi>Teacher</hi> for thee, and to the Lord muſt thou give an account for thy <hi>ſelf,</hi> therefore look well to thy ſtanding; interpret for thy ſelf, and beleeve for thy ſelf, and let not thoſe <hi>Dreamers</hi> that call themſelves <hi>Gods Meſſengers and Interpreters</hi> (but live in pride, malice, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) lead thee down hood-winck'd to the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of death, whence there is no returning.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>16.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I now come to your ſixteenth Section, in which you follow your old trade of deceit, <hi>viz.</hi> not daring to deny in expreſs terms (although you do in effect) Chriſts unlimited prohibition,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:168420:27"/>of <hi>ſwearing at all;</hi> you fall from that, to asking me queſtions. Before I anſwer which,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.34. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> "ΟΛΩΣ.</note> I cannot but take notice of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambular Obſervations. 1. You ſuggeſt that the <hi>Founders of the Quakers Religion</hi> (as you expreſs it) <hi>are ſuppoſed to be Papiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> This is ſuch a ridiculous ſuggeſtion that the like I have ſeldom met with. I have been a diligent inquirer into the principles, profeſſions, lives, and converſations, of that <hi>deſpiſed</hi> people; and upon inquiry do find, that there is not a people in the world who in all theſe, do more directly ſtrike at the very <hi>root</hi> of Popery, then they do, and yet the delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Teachers of this Nation, do (hoping thereby to contract an odium upon them among the ſimple) cry out, O they are many of them <hi>Jeſuites</hi> and <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Sure I am, it's no difficult thing to prove the greateſt part of your <hi>Steeple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe-worſhip</hi> to be but refined Popery. 2. I ſay, that ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the <hi>Contents of a Book,</hi> and kiſſing a Book, is a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, popiſh invention, and that which was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver practiced by the Saints of old, whilſt ſwearing was in force.</p>
               <p>The ſum of your two firſt Queries to me is, <hi>Whether Christ ſpake or intended any thing, which might claſh with the commands of God? or whether he did forbid any part of Gods moral worſhip?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> But that the Lord in juſt judgement upon you for fighting againſt the truth, hath given you up to blindneſs of heart; could one almoſt imagine, that two that pretend themſelves able Schollars, and eminent Chriſtians, ſhould propoſe Queries that have not the leaſt ſhadow and weight of reaſon in them? May you not on the ſame ground charge Chriſt with <hi>claſhing with Gods commands,</hi> in putting an end to all the Iewiſh <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies?</hi> was not the practice of their whole worſhip, taken up by expreſs <hi>command</hi> from God,<note place="margin">Exod. 30.28. Lev. 6.18, 22. Lev. 23.13, 14 Exod. 28.42, 43. Gen. 17.13.</note> conſiſting in <hi>waſhings, meat-offerings, drink-offerings,</hi> the <hi>Prieſts veſtments, Sacrifices, Circumciſion,</hi> &amp;c. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning moſt of which, and many other <hi>Rites</hi> it's ſaid by the Lord (which I never read of ſwearing) that they <hi>ſhould be Statutes for EVER, throughout ALL generations?</hi> and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:168420:27"/>yet Chriſt cometh and aboliſheth all theſe, and not <hi>claſh with his Fathers commands;</hi> Was not Circumciſion com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded upon that ſevere penalty, of being <hi>cut off from the people,</hi> in caſe of not being circumciſed?<note place="margin">Gen. 17 14. Gal. 5.2.</note> and yet <hi>Paul</hi> telleth the <hi>Galathians,</hi> that if they were <hi>circumciſed Chriſt ſhould profit them nothing.</hi> There is a time when it is death not to circumciſe, and there is a time when <hi>Paul</hi> maketh it more then death to uſe it. Chriſt in like manner, yeeldeth by way of conceſſion, that there <hi>was</hi> a ſeaſon when ſwearing was lawfully uſed,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.33, 34.</note> 
                  <hi>but I ſay unto you (NOW) ſwear not at all.</hi> And if he ſay it, ſure I am, it is not for you to diſpute his commands; for it was not onely decreed in heaven, but by the Lords own mouth proclaimed on earth, that he is his <hi>beloved Son,</hi> and that him ſhould <hi>all men HEAR.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 17 5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>What you ſay touching the neceſſity of Oathes to decide controverſies, is but a lame begging of the queſtion; for, there can be no real neceſſity ſuppoſed for that, which Chriſt (the great <hi>Law-giver</hi>) <hi>forbiddeth</hi> the uſe of.<note place="margin">Heb. 6.16.</note> That the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> ſaith, that an <hi>oath for confirmation, is to men an end of all ſtrife,</hi> is true: To which I reply three things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That Author writeth to the Hebrews (among whom ſwearing was firſt practiſed) by way of conceſſion, that it was uſed among them (who were probably ignorant of the <hi>change</hi> of the <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> and conſequently of the <hi>repeal</hi> of that practife) for that purpoſe, but he doth neither <hi>command</hi> it, nor <hi>commend</hi> it.</item>
                  <item>2. In that he ſaith that to <hi>men,</hi> it is an <hi>end</hi> of ſtrife; it is even thence clear, that to them who are already come to the <hi>end</hi> of all ſtrife (being redeemed out of it) an oath is uſeleſs.</item>
                  <item>3. But laſtly, if this Author, or an <hi>Angel</hi> from Heaven, had commanded men to <hi>ſwear,</hi> yet behold a <hi>greater</hi> then the Author to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> a greater then <hi>Moſes,</hi> a <hi>greater</hi> then the Angels (whom the Father com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth to <hi>worſhip him</hi>) is <hi>here,</hi> who ſaith,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.6.</note> 
                     <hi>ſwear not AT ALL.</hi> And <hi>him</hi> are we all commanded <hi>to hear, in all things whatſoever he ſhall ſay unto us. And every ſoul which will not hear</hi> him, <hi>ſhall be deſtroyed from among the people,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 18.15.</note> ſaith
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:168420:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Spirit of the Lord,<note place="margin">Act 3.22 23.</note> by the mouth of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>That prejudice you ſuggeſt to which <hi>mens Eſtates would be liable by cheating companions,</hi> in caſe there were no ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is of no force; for he that will (contrary to the witneſs of God in his conſcience) <hi>ſay</hi> a thing falſly, will not ſtick to <hi>ſwear</hi> it: And he that can affirm or deny a thing falſly with his <hi>yea, yea, nay, nay,</hi> will not ſcruple to ſeal the ſame with his <hi>oath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the examples you offer of <hi>Abrahams requiring an oath of his ſervant,</hi> Jacob <hi>of</hi> Joſeph, Nehemiah <hi>of the</hi> Jews; they all fall to the ground (with Circumciſion, and other <hi>Rites</hi> practiſed by the ſame perſons) not onely by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but the countermand of the great Law-giver, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of which being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to your ſelves, you paſs from them, and in your cloſing Query (by which you thought to have ſtruck me ſilent) do confidently demand of me, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Apoſtle <hi>Paul did well or ill to ſwear,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Behold,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 1.20.</note> 
                  <hi>before God I lie not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Monſtrous impiety! matchleſs impudence! What? was it not ſufficient for you to clip, and mince, the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of Chriſt, but you muſt audaciouſly attempt to faſten a ſlanderous accuſation upon innocent <hi>Paul,</hi> by charging him for a ſwearer?<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Is <hi>Pauls</hi> ſaying, <hi>before God,</hi> any more then in the <hi>preſence</hi> of God, or in the <hi>ſight</hi> of God? Do you not know (which induceth me to beleeve that you ſin againſt the light of Chriſt in your conſciences) that the ſame Greek word is uſed to ſignifie ſo in more then twenty places of the Scripture?<note place="margin">Luke 15.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Doth not <hi>Luke</hi> uſe the ſame word when he ſaith, that there <hi>is joy in the PRESENCE of the Angels, over one repenting ſinner.</hi> Doth not the ſame Evangeliſt uſe the ſame word for,<note place="margin">Luk. 1.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>in conſpeclu meo</hi> Gen 17.1.</note> in the ſight of God, ſaying, touching <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> that <hi>he ſhould be great in the SIGHT of the Lord?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doth not God command <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſaying, <hi>walk BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORE me, and be thou perfect;</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> commend <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> for being <hi>both righteous BEFORE
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:168420:28"/>God?</hi> And did God and <hi>Luke ſwear</hi> in theſe ſayings?<note place="margin">Luk. 1.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, by this blaſphemous doctrine of yours, how will you abſolve Chriſt himſelf from being a ſwearer? who (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other inſtances in Scripture) doth uſe the ſame expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion three times in one Chapter, ſaying of the Sparrows,<note place="margin">Luk 12.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that <hi>not one of them is forgotten BEFORE God.</hi> And further, he <hi>that denieth me BEFORE men, ſhall be denied BEFORE the Angels of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And do you not bluſh to think, muchleſs to ſay, that Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> did here <hi>ſwear</hi> by his Father, or <hi>ſwear</hi> by men, or <hi>ſwear</hi> by the Angels of God? I could tire the patience of the Reader with inſtances of this nature. By which all the wiſe in heart may judge, what a loathſom ſpirit that is, by which you are acted, who durſt in print belye <hi>Paul,</hi> and blaſpheme the Son of God, by leaving them upon record under your own hands for <hi>ſwearers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>17.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Now to palliate this your contradiction to Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in your ſeventeenth Section you undertake to expound Chriſts prohibition of ſwearing, extending it to our <hi>ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſcourſe;</hi> but <hi>before a Magiſtrate</hi> you aſſert it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>ſwear not AT ALL. Chriſtopher Fowler</hi> and <hi>Simon Ford</hi> ſay nay, but before a Magiſtrate you may ſwear: Now whether Chriſt or they are to be beleeved, let all that fear the Lord judge. Suppoſe one of your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſhould ask you leave to paſs to <hi>London</hi> on <hi>horſeback,</hi> you tell him nay; he asketh again, ſhall I go by <hi>coach</hi> or on <hi>foot;</hi> you reply nay, thou ſhalt not go <hi>at all.</hi> If this ſervant ſhall, notwithſtanding this prohibition, preſume to paſs to <hi>London</hi> by <hi>water,</hi> whether will you not eſteem him diſobedient, having given him a <hi>univerſal</hi> denial, although he was not particularly forbidden to paſs by <hi>water.</hi> The application is obvious to thoſe that are ſerious.</p>
               <p>You tell your Reader in the cloſe of your ſixteenth Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that <hi>this doctrine of the unlawfulneſs of ſwearing in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:168420:29"/>any caſe, is a fragment of the old German Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Were Chriſt, and the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> German Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, who do expreſly forbid men <hi>to ſwear at all,</hi> or by <hi>any manner of oath?</hi> But what would you inſer thence? why this, that <hi>it concerneth me to look to it, that (as the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates then ſaw cauſe to diſpute with the ſword of juſtice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, ſo) the Magiſtracy of</hi> England <hi>may never have the like provocation, to do the ſame againſt the Quakers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sectaries among us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Mind Reader, what ſpirit theſe men are of, and what they hunt after,<note place="margin">Aut Caeſares aut nulli.</note> blood, blood, <hi>Quakers</hi> and other <hi>Sectaries?</hi> That is to ſay, all thoſe that cannot ſubject their neeks to the Prieſts yoke. But ſtay, Sirs, was it a <hi>Quaker,</hi> or <hi>Sectary,</hi> or was it a Prieſt that loſt his head by the <hi>Sword of Juſtice</hi> upon Tower-hill?<note place="margin">Chriſtoph. Love</note> Were both your hands clean from the wickedneſs of that bloody deſign? if they were, its well. But ſure I am that ſo conſiderable a number of your impericus generation, were concerned in that piece of Treaſon, that had the State <hi>diſputed</hi> it with you according to the provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion given them, they might have found ſufficient cauſe to have cut many a Prieſt in this Nation ſhorter by the head.</p>
               <p>And being now engaged in this diſcourſe, I cannot but freely declare my mind to the whole Nation in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, <hi>viz.</hi> all <hi>plots</hi> and deſigns, together with all <hi>plotters</hi> and deſigners, againſt the peace of the State under which they live, I do utterly <hi>deny;</hi> for <hi>the grace of God which bringeth ſalvation, teacheth</hi> me to live <hi>peaceably</hi> and <hi>ſoberly,</hi> in this preſent evil world.</p>
               <p>And be they of what name or profeſſion ſoever, that are found agitating any deſign for the ſpilling of <hi>blood,</hi> let the hand of juſtice find them out, and let them reap that juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that is according to their doings. And whatever theſe men of blood (whoſe ambition it is to have their ſeet upon all others necks) do ſuggeſt to the Magiſtrate, yet I can freely ſay, that I do not know any one perſon in the Nation called a <hi>Quaker,</hi> but will readily ſet his ſeal to what I have now declared.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:168420:29"/>
               <p>I have been the larger in this particular about <hi>ſwearing</hi> becauſe of that great (but groundleſs) flouriſh you make in the cloſe of your ſeventeenth Section touching it, <hi>viz.</hi> that who ſo can <hi>reconcile Chriſts prohibition,</hi> to <hi>the precepts and examples</hi> quoted by you, <hi>ſhall gain the cauſe;</hi> a thing ſo eaſily effected, that there is none, but he that is wilfully blind, but will ſee the ſeeming diſcord, fully reconciled by what hath been before ſaid.</p>
               <p>All that <hi>William Thomas</hi> doth about this particular, in mangling and confounding Chriſts plain precept, and clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that of the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> by leaving out in his quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation thoſe words, <hi>nor by any other oath;</hi> I ſay,<note place="margin">Jam. 5.12.</note> it's all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly anſwered before, and not onely his <hi>creature-ſwearing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 25.</note> and his <hi>common ſwearing</hi> (as he expreſſeth himſelf) but all <hi>ſwearing</hi> falleth to the ground by that univerſal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of Chriſts, <hi>ſwear not at all.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>18.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your eighteenth Section is made up of fained words, and falſe ſuggeſtions; when you have a mind to belie me, then you quote not my particular expreſſions, but tell your Reader that the <hi>ſum and upſhot</hi> of them is ſuch and ſuch; and ſo inſtead of my words, do produce the idle concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of your own brains, and then ſpend time to anſwer them; juſt like children that fight with their own ſhadows. You pretend to have a great weight upon your ſhoulders, whilſt you own the work of <hi>builders,</hi> but it is but of <hi>Babel; Sowers, viz.</hi> of <hi>tares,</hi> ſtrife, and ſedition among men; <hi>Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> but it is of that which muſt be <hi>pluck'd</hi> up; <hi>Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and yet briars, and thorns ſtill ſtanding in your fields; <hi>Shepheards,</hi> but not Chriſts, for they never <hi>devoured</hi> the ſheep; <hi>Watchmen,</hi> but very <hi>blind</hi> ones; <hi>Souldiers,</hi> but not under Chriſts Banner, for ſuch fought not with <hi>carnal wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons;</hi> I doubt not but you have a good mind to this laſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, had you but an opportunity to fight Presbytery into the Chair.</p>
               <p>You tell me in the ſame Section, that it's my <hi>Law, that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:168420:30"/>thoſe that have been bred to ſtudy, muſt have no ſubſiſtence, but by handy work or begging.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> What a yoak of impudent Liars are you, who durſt in print to father that expreſſion upon me, which never procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of my lip? If you preach lies to the people, with that confidence with which you print them; let all that fear the Lord judge what <hi>maeſter</hi> you ſerve, whoſe Miniſters you are, and whom you may call your <hi>Father.</hi> That it is your declared doubt, that you ſhould be reduced to <hi>beg</hi> or <hi>work,</hi> in caſe you had not your maintenance aſcertained to you, is clear to all that obſerve any thing for why elſe is it that you do make ſuch firm <hi>indentures</hi> with the people for your wages, before ye dare enter upon the work? At the cloſe of this Section you ſeem to lament the hard meaſure you ſhould have from me, in <hi>caſe, I could compaſſe my fifth Monarchy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> This ſuggeſtion hath been once offered before, and now repeated, to beget (if poſſible) a jealous eye in the State upon a people trodden down, and trampled upon in the ſtreets by all, and who are as far removed from a ſpirit of fighting, as theſe men are from the Spirit of truth, which is as far as light from darkneſs, or Heaven from Hell. And therefore I tell you again, that I do neither own, nor expect any other fifth Monarchy but this, that Chriſt Jeſus ſhould rule and reign in the <hi>contrite heart,</hi> which is already begun in the hearts of thouſands in this Nation.</p>
               <p>You further boaſt how you ſhould <hi>truſt</hi> God in caſe you were reduced to that <hi>condition,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> What admirable faith have theſe men, who can ſpeak ſo largely of truſting God for food and raiment, with <hi>full</hi> bellies, and well-<hi>clothed</hi> backs? and have firm depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on him for their maintenance, whilſt their bags and barns are well <hi>filled,</hi> and have a power from without to force the people, where they will not freely give down their milk.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>19.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>You entertain your Reader in your nineteenth Section
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:168420:30"/>with a few jeſts, and then come in the cloſe to <hi>bleſſe God</hi> that <hi>provides for you;</hi> telling your Reader, that you <hi>dare not take Gods gifts, and throw them back into his face, by contemning the gracious allowance of his providence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Is the tenth of poor mens labours that you cruelly exact from them, the <hi>gift of God?</hi> and is your forced main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance which you tear out of peoples throats, the <hi>gracious allowance of his providence?</hi> Was this the reaſon why one of<note n="*" place="margin">Chriſtopher Fowler.</note> you did arreſt ſeveral poor Gardners in <hi>Redding</hi> (to the number of twelve, as I am informed) for the Tithe of their <hi>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNEPS and CARRETS;</hi> that he might thereby quit himſelf from the guilt of <hi>throwing Gods gifts in his face?</hi> &amp;c. Do not think to cover over the venom of your hearts and practiſes, with ſuch hypocritical pretences as theſe; and know, that although you may for a ſeaſon blind the eyes of <hi>men,</hi> with ſuch miſts of the bottomleſs pit, yet the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hand of the <hi>all-ſeeing God</hi> will find you out, and ſurely reward you according to the wickedneſs of your doings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>20.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And now I am come to deal with you touching your great Idoll, <hi>Tithes,</hi> about which you and <hi>William Thomas</hi> make a great cry, as they in behalf of their <hi>dead</hi> Goddeſs,<note place="margin">Acts 19.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Great is Diana of the Epheſians</hi> but prove nothing. Sometimes you flie to the example of <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> for patronage in your requiring Tithes, ſometimes to the <hi>Law of man.</hi> And becauſe you judge it too <hi>Jewiſh</hi> to claim them as Succeſſors to <hi>Levi</hi> (though Gods command for Tithes, and the inſtitution of that Prieſthood were of equall antiquity) you run thence to <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> his receiving them of <hi>Abram,</hi> hoping thence to gain ſomething for a covering to your practiſes not at all warranted by any example of the Miniſters of Chriſt in the Scripture. But if this be the firmeſt prop you have to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port your <hi>Idol</hi> (and upon that you lay the ſtreſs of your ſwelling Argument in your 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Section) I doubt not but by what followeth, the underſtanding Reader will conclude, that its no more able to ſtand before the ſtrength of truth, then
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:168420:31"/>
                  <hi>Dagon</hi> was <hi>before the Ark of God</hi> And therefore to all that you have pleaded in the behalf of Tythes,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 5.4.</note> from your Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth to the end of your Twenty eighth Section, I ſhall make my reply in theſe following particular.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1.<note place="margin">Heb. 7.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Abram</hi> returning from the ſlaughter of certain Kings, <hi>GAVE unto Melchiſedeck</hi> (who came out to <hi>meet</hi> him) <hi>the tenth of his SPOILS</hi> taken in the War. The Scripture ſaith not, that he gave them the tenth of his <hi>enereaſe,</hi> the tenth <hi>Calf,</hi> the tenth <hi>Lamb,</hi> the tenth <hi>Sheaf,</hi> the tenth <hi>Pig, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2.<note place="margin">Gen. 28.22.</note> We read not that <hi>Abram</hi> did this by any command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords, but as a free will-offering (ſuch as was <hi>Jacobs</hi> vow) neither do the Scripture ſay that <hi>Melchiſedeck required</hi> or <hi>exacted</hi> theſe ſpoils of <hi>Abram,</hi> but that they were <hi>voluntarily</hi> given him.</item>
                  <item>3. You cannot ſhew in Scripture that the tenth of <hi>ſpoils</hi> was <hi>Melchiſedecks yearly</hi> maintenance, or that <hi>Abraham</hi> gave them to him more then <hi>once.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4.<note place="margin">Gen. 14 18, 19</note> 
                     <hi>Abram</hi> gave the tenth of his <hi>ſpoils</hi> to <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> from whom he received a <hi>bleſſing,</hi> beſides <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>wine</hi> he <hi>brought forth</hi> to him; but you do forcibly <hi>extort</hi> the tenth of all their encreaſe from them; on whom you pronounce the <hi>curſe,</hi> whom ye <hi>revile,</hi> againſt whom ye <hi>rail,</hi> and of whom you ſpeak all manner of <hi>evil.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. Who made you Prieſts <hi>after the order of Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck;</hi> or how came you to be his ſucceſſors; who have as much right to his Prieſthood, as the Biſhops and their crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures had to make Miniſters for Jeſus Chriſt?</item>
               </list>
               <p>By all which, the wiſe-hearted Reader may perceive, that the example of <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> (under which you ſeem ſo ſecurely to ſhelter your ſelves) doth not afford you the leaſt ſhadow of countenance in your ungoſpel-like practices, in commencing ſuits at law againſt-men for the tenth of all their encreaſe. For let all men judge what parallel there is; <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> the Prieſt of the moſt high God, meeteth <hi>Abram</hi> returning from the War, <hi>bleſſeth him, receiveth</hi> (not exacteth) and that (not as his <hi>ſtanding</hi> maintenance) but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:168420:31"/>
                  <hi>once,</hi> the tenth (not of all his encreaſe but) of his <hi>ſpoils,</hi> which <hi>Abram</hi> (not by commandment but) voluntarily <hi>gave</hi> him. But <hi>you</hi> (who are not Prieſts, as was <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedeck</hi>) do demand and <hi>force</hi> for your <hi>yearly</hi> maintenance during <hi>life,</hi> from whole Pariſhes (even where you <hi>curſe</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of bleſſing) the tenth of all their encreaſe. So that the ſtrongeſt inference that can be drawn from this example is this; that when any King returneth from the War, if he meet with a Prieſt of the moſt high God that <hi>bleſſeth</hi> him, he may, if he pleaſe, <hi>give</hi> him the tenth of his <hi>ſpoils;</hi> and what is this to you? unleſs you can perſwade the Protector to grant, that when the Army or Fleet, do return from War, you meeting them with <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>wine</hi> (which I ſcarce beleeve you will do, for moſt of you do not love them ſo well) may receive the tenth of all their <hi>ſpoils.</hi> But what a mighty ſlaughter of Kings muſt the Army and Fleet needs make, to gain ſo much <hi>ſpoil,</hi> the tenth of which muſt ſerve to be a ſtanding maintenance to ſo many Prieſts, who live ſo high, and fare ſo deliciouſly, as the moſt of you do?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>24.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Whereas you urge that Tythes are <hi>due to Chriſt,</hi> being a <hi>Prieſt after the order of Melchiſedeck</hi> (and therefore due to you) it is ſuch a ridiculous fiction, as the like I have ſeldom heard. For would Chriſt never have made demand of that which was his <hi>due,</hi> nor his Apoſtles and Miniſters after him? As he and they were faithful in telling the people of other their abominations, ſo ſurely they would not have been ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and not (at leaſt) have <hi>told</hi> them of their <hi>duty,</hi> and reproved them for their <hi>ſin,</hi> in detaining from them the tenth of their encreaſe, which was their <hi>due</hi> by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
               <p>But you ſay <hi>the Miniſters of Chriſt then</hi> had not the <hi>ſame legal right, back'd with the power of a Chriſtan Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:168420:32"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> To which I reply two things. 1: Could they not have made demand without a Magiſtrate, and have laid it as a ſin upon thoſe that refuſed payment? 2. But this is of no weight. for neither had the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> any law to <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force</hi> payment at all; which maketh your practice the more wicked, who (ſuppoſing Tythes to be as due to you as to <hi>Levi</hi>) do notwithſtanding horribly tranſgreſs their pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, in extorting that by <hi>Law</hi> from the people, of which they onely made demand, by vertue of Gods appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>I ſhall cloſe this of Tythes with theſe four things. 1. I do demand of you, and <hi>William Thomas,</hi> and of every Tyth-gathering Teacher in <hi>England,</hi> but one example throughout the Scripture, either of a Prieſt under the Law, or of any Miniſter of the Goſpel ſince Chriſt, that did ever <hi>force</hi> his maintenance from the people, nay, even <hi>that</hi> maintenance which was given them by Gods, or Chriſt?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas there was but a <hi>tenth</hi> appointed payable to the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> and a <hi>tenth</hi> given to <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> how cometh it to paſs, that you (who are not of that Tribe) do demand, and receive a <hi>ſeventh</hi> of the people, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>ſeventh</hi> Calf, a <hi>ſeventh</hi> Lamb, a <hi>ſeventh</hi> Pig? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. I would demand of <hi>William Thomas,</hi> whether he did not ſome years ſince, receive of his Pariſhoners the <hi>ſixth part</hi> of all their encreaſe for one year? and whether he did not urge them to have continued the ſame for one year <hi>more,</hi> which they refuſed? if this be true in the matter of <hi>fact</hi> (for which I can produce teſtimony out of his own neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood) then I demand, what ſhadow of a rule in Scripture, he had for this? and whether (ſuppoſing the tenth to be his due) it be not extortion to receive the <hi>ſixth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Laſtly, There is no clearer demonſtration that neither you nor he, are Miniſters of Chriſt, then this, that you expreſs ſuch clamour about your maintenance. What fears? What di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſts? what out-crys? Chriſt is no <hi>hard Maſter,</hi> for where he ſendeth out, although it be without <hi>purſe,</hi> or <hi>ſcrip, &amp;c.</hi> there is no want: Never any that were faithful in his work
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:168420:32"/>but had enough; and were you his ſervants you would truſt more, and fear and complain leſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>29.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>To the contents of your twenty ninth Section, treating a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout your not <hi>truſting your Maſter</hi> (as his Miniſters in Scripture did) but <hi>indenting</hi> for a maintenance, I have already made reply in my ſeventh Section, to which I refer the Reader.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>30.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In this Section you charge me with <hi>bold cenſures,</hi> becauſe I charge it as hypocriſie on ſuch as <hi>preach againſt pride, and yet live in it, againſt covetouſneſs,</hi> and yet <hi>are greedy of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy lucre &amp;c.</hi> And you do paſſionately deny that matter of fact. Whereas ſhould I charge you two in particular to be a couple of <hi>proud, imperious, domineering</hi> perſons, I could ſoon produce many ſcores of witneſſes, out of the Town of <hi>Reading,</hi> and the County of <hi>Berks,</hi> to give teſtimony there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. And as to the moſt of your Brethren abroad, who, but he that ſhutteth his eyes at noon day, doth not ſee that whilſt they preach againſt pride, and covetouſneſs, they themſelves are both proud and covetous? who more haughty? who more <hi>greedy of filthy lucre?</hi> I do further charge it as groſs hypocriſie, for men to come in the face of a congregation, pretending to pray with a great deal of zeal, that God would <hi>teach them what to ſay,</hi> when as they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved <hi>before hand</hi> what they will ſay. And I do further ask you, where you read of any of the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt in Scripture, that carried about Sermon-notes in their pockets, to the ſeveral places where they preached the Goſpel, and putting them in a book, did now and then read, and now and then ſpeak a few ſentences to the people without them? Or whether did they not occaſionally where they came, ſpeak as the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the Lord gave them <hi>utterance?</hi> Surely, were they now upon the earth, <hi>William Thomas</hi> would damn them
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:168420:33"/>for extemporary Teachers,<note place="margin">Page 40.</note> and <hi>Enthuſiaſts,</hi> as in the heighth of his rage, he doth thoſe that have not Sermon-notes, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>31.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>You charge me in your following Section, with bringing an Indictment of felony againſt poor Miniſters (as you call them) for <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>OTING of the Fathers, and Expoſiters of Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep</hi> But that you are accuſtomed to tell your Reader that I ſay this and that, which never proceeded out of my lips (thereby hoping to enervate the force of that truth which I did indeed ſpeak) one would wonder that you ſhould ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudently aſſert ſo manifeſt a lye touching me: Let the honeſt Reader peruſe my whole Epiſtle, and ſee if there be ſuch a word as <hi>quote</hi> or <hi>quoting,</hi> to be found therein. And yet I muſt needs be made to charge your poor Miniſters, with that which I never ſaid. And having laid a lye for your foundation, you proceed to erect thereon a rotten build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; propoſing ſeveral lofty interrogatories to me, touching <hi>Chriſt quoting Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets, Peter quoting Paul;</hi> and <hi>Paul quoting Aratus, Menander,</hi> and <hi>Epimenides;</hi> and all this while do but fight againſt a lye of your own creating, for I never gain-ſaid any of theſe things. You know well enough, that my tenth Article did expreſs the complaint made by your generation, againſt the people called Quakers, for that they called thoſe men <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Robbers</hi> who did <hi>spend ſix days in the week to gather together the words of other men,</hi> and then <hi>come forth on the ſeventh day,</hi> and bid the <hi>people hearken to the word of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> And did Chriſt or the Apoſtles thus? they ſpake from the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and preach'd by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and as they were by <hi>that</hi> directed, they did (where they ſaw occaſion) urge the words of the Prophets, againſt thoſe that talked of them, but dwelt in that Spirit that ſlew them, as your generation do at this day, preach Chriſt in <hi>words,</hi> but yet crucifie him where he appeareth in <hi>power.</hi> And this practice of Chriſt and the Apoſtles I never condemned</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:168420:33"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Thomas</hi> ſoming out his rage about this Article,<note place="margin">Page 42.</note> is as foul and falſe in his ſlanderous accuſations, as you. He confeſſeth that he doth <hi>spend</hi> his <hi>time to gather together the words of the Prophets and Apoſtles (with their right mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings)</hi> and then ſay, <hi>Hearken unto the word of the Lord.</hi> Where by the way we muſt obſerve, that the meanings that the Prieſts do put upon the words of the Prophets and Apoſtles, are by this man eſteemed the <hi>word of the Lord.</hi> And then demandeth whether they be <hi>theeves, becauſe</hi> they <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that from the Lord which</hi> they <hi>deliver to his people?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> He is not in the account of truth a <hi>Thief,</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth that from the Lord, that he delivereth to the people. But muſt he that maketh it his trade to gather together the Saints words, and thereunto add his own imaginations, and then come forth and bid the people hearken to the word of the Lord, I ſay, muſt this man preſently be ſaid to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this from the Lord?</hi> when as whilſt he talketh of the Saints words, he is a ſtranger to the Saints conditions, and an enemy to thoſe that witneſs them? may not the worſt of men, nay, the fowleſt of Devils, gather together the Saints words and the meanings of men impoſed upon them, and then talk of them to the people? and will he allow that theſe Brats of darkneſs do therein ſpeak what they receive <hi>from the Lord,</hi> or that the <hi>word</hi> of the Lord <hi>cometh</hi> unto <hi>them?</hi> Grant but his irrational premiſes, and this diſmal concluſion will unavoidably follow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>32.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In this Section you ſhufflle off your Reader (according to your uſual manner of anſwering) with a few ſcoffs and Queries; and ſuch alſo, which are not at all to the thing in hand. My Article ſpake of the people called Quakers, their <hi>confident adviſing the</hi> Publick Teachers <hi>to preach no more to the people, then the Lord hath ſpoken to them.</hi> In anſwer to which, you fall to querying about <hi>Propheteſſes</hi> and <hi>womens teaching,</hi> and others <hi>coming</hi> into your <hi>Congregations;</hi> and <hi>Chriſts,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles diſputing in the Synagogues, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:168420:34"/>All which were ſubjects that my Article ſpake not of. But wanting matter of juſt quarrel or accuſation againſt me (the Article being plain) you would ſeek to create ſome. To all which your filty ſcoffs, and impertinent Queries, I ſhall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay Three things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1.<note place="margin">Gal. 3.28.</note> The Spirit of the Lord is not confined to one Sex, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is <hi>there male or female in Chriſt Jeſus, but all are one.</hi> Had learned <hi>Apollos</hi> been ſuch a ſtubborn opinioniſt as you ſcorners are, he would have diſdained (as you do) to have received inſtruction, from the lips of a poor <hi>Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilla.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Although Chriſt, and the Apoſtles did preach down the whole pedagogy of the Jews, and all their Temple-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (for which they were ſo exceeding zealous) yet when they came into their <hi>Synagogues</hi> to diſpute with them, they found even at <hi>their</hi> hands, a thouſand times ſairer quarter, then many poor hearts finde from your Wolfiſh flocks in your Steeple-houſes, for ſpeaking but ſix words, among whom, they are oftentimes in danger of <hi>life,</hi> or <hi>limb.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Whereas you ſpeak of the Quakers violating that <hi>Article of the Government</hi> which alloweth <hi>liberty to all ſuch as profeſs Faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> I ſay, that this is monſtrous hypocriſie in you; when as that Article of the <hi>Government,</hi> is not more broken upon any order of men at this day in the Nation, then upon that ſuffering people called Quakers; and that by the hands of the Prieſts Diſciples, and their perſecuting companions; by coming into their peacable meetings, and there railing, and reviling them, nay oftentimes laying vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent hands on them; of which there is ſcarce a day but doth afford an inſtance in ſome part of this Nation or other? and do <hi>you,</hi> as the moſt guilty, begin to complain firſt?</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>33.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your Three and thirtieth Section is ſuch a Linſy. woolſey peece, ſuch a medly of confuſion, that there is neither head not tail in it. The advice given you, <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>preach no more to the people then the Lord hath ſpoken to you,</hi> you ſay, <hi>were it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:168420:34"/>to</hi> you <hi>in a ſober, private, Chriſtian way</hi> (I do well know you love to be honored before the people) <hi>you would take well at my hands, and practice accordingly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Then you approve of the advice as good. And why is it then that you endeavour in the remaining part of your Section to contradict it, and go about to perſwade your Reader, that I bad mal-adviſed you, in <hi>meaning</hi> what I did not ſpeak? It's a ſtrange law, that when no fault can be found with a mans <hi>words,</hi> being wholeſom, he muſt then be reviled, and beaten, for his ſuppoſed meanings. You further demand of me, to what <hi>purpoſe the Scripture is avouched to be profitable for doctrine, if you may raiſe no doctrines from it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> With what reaſon, or on what ground this imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent Query is propoſed (more then to ſpend your ſpare time) I profeſs I cannot conceive, for that there is nothing ſpoken in my Article that concerneth any ſuch thing. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſince you will needs know my mind in the caſe, I ſay, That the <hi>holy</hi> Scriptures were given <hi>by inſpiration</hi> of God,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16.</note> and are <hi>profitable</hi> for <hi>doctrine, reproof,</hi> and <hi>correction,</hi> is true; but doth it therefore follow that the Scriptures were given forth, for you by the ſtrength of your imaginations, to raiſe <hi>Doctrines, Reaſons,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes</hi> from them, and then take them &amp; ſell them to the people for mony? The Scriptures of truth, as they were ſpoken forth by the <hi>holy men of God,</hi> are pure, but you and your Brethren (to gain a livelihood thereby) do ſpend your time to faſten your own corrupt gloſſes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations upon them, in which you are ſo full of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and contradictions each to other, that, that which hath in it ſelf a ſweet <hi>harmony,</hi> you make to be a monſtrous heap of <hi>jars</hi> and <hi>diſcord:</hi> Your after diſcourſe about <hi>Chriſts</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſpeaking the <hi>words of Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> is vain and frivolous; being that which I never denied, or condemned. And therefore you have done but as peeviſh perſons, in a deep fit of melancholly, <hi>viz.</hi> create images in your own fancies, and then fight with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:168420:35"/>
               <head>SECT. <hi>34.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In this Section you ſtudy how to pick matter of wrangling, about that advice given you, <hi>To preach no more to the people then you your ſelves witneſs the life and power of within your ſelves.</hi> But finding my expreſſions plain, you fall (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your wonted ingenuous way) to ſuppoſe meanings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my naked expreſſions. And my meaning muſt needs be ſuppoſed to be that which never came out of my lips: The ground of this is, becauſe you ſay <hi>others of</hi> my <hi>brethren</hi> do ſo, and ſo. How is that proved? by <hi>a diſcourſe had</hi> (you ſay) <hi>betwixt two Quakers related by</hi> John Toldervy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> You appeal to Col <hi>Sidenham</hi> in your fawning Epiſtle touching your <hi>candor and integrity</hi> in the <hi>managery</hi> (a very hard word) as you term it, of your anſwer to my Epiſtle. And is this one of the demonſtrations of your <hi>candor</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity,</hi> to charge ſuch and ſuch things upon the people cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Quakers, and then offer <hi>John Toldervy</hi> for proof? this is juſt as if a man ſhould have come to the <hi>Chief-Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> of old, and asked them, is Chriſt an evil-doer, and worthy to be given over to be <hi>crucified?</hi> yea would they ſay, how is that proved? Why, <hi>Judas</hi> ſaith ſo. And then ask the people of the Jews, what is this Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth?</hi> why, would they ſay, he is a <hi>deceiver,</hi> and a <hi>blaſphemer;</hi> how is that proved? Our <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Chief-Prieſts</hi> ſay ſo. And ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>John Toldervy,</hi> the innocent ſhall no way eſcape condemnation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>35.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your 35<hi rend="sup">th</hi> is made up of malicious ſlanders, and falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations; where are thoſe <hi>lazie Lurdens,</hi> or <hi>Drones</hi> (as you call them) <hi>who eat the fat,</hi> and <hi>drink the ſweet?</hi> For mine own part, I know none ſuch but the Prieſts; who yet are wiſer for themſelves, then thoſe you accuſe of <hi>walking up and down the Land;</hi> for that inſtead of travelling through heat, and cold, drouth and wet, they love to keep cloſe in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:168420:35"/>one pariſh, <hi>to eat the fat, and drink the ſweet.</hi> But where are thoſe that do <hi>eat their wives and families out of doors?</hi> name any man that's called a Quaker, that hath done ſo; and if you can (were recrimination any excuſe) I doubt not but for every ſuch <hi>one,</hi> to name you <hi>twenty</hi> Prieſts that are deeply guilty of the ſame crime.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>36.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In your 36<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Section you accuſe me of <hi>ſetting up the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Spirit, in oppoſition to all humane ſtudies;</hi> and why? Becauſe my Twelfth Article ſaid, <hi>That the mind of God is not to be known by ſtudy in a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, but by reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Spirit,</hi> who alone <hi>knoweth his mind.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.11, 12</note> And is not this plain <hi>truth?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>37.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Why is it then, that you make ſuch a great noiſe about <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity learning;</hi> endeavouring to make <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> to be Advocates for you in the caſe? The firſt of whom, <hi>viz, Paul,</hi> did with all his learning <hi>fight</hi> againſt Chriſt, and drew his blood; as you, and many others at this day do, that pretend highly to it. And although he came afterwards to know and receive, that Jeſus whom he before perſecuted, yet, I deny it was at all by the power of his <hi>humane learning,</hi> but by the <hi>revelation of the Spirit</hi> of life. And as for <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> how could you but bluſh (were you not paſt all ſhame) to abuſe and belie him as you do, in bringing him for teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the <hi>uſefulneſs of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity learning</hi> in this way; making him to ſay, that in the <hi>reading of the Scriptures</hi> it <hi>may keep a man from wreſting them to destruction?</hi> doth not the Scripture bear witneſs of <hi>Peter,</hi> that he himſelf was unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? and will you make <hi>Peter</hi> to condemn <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act 4.13.</note> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitly conclude that he himſelf was a <hi>wreſter</hi> of Scripture having not that <hi>learning,</hi> which you ſay will <hi>keep men from wreſting them?</hi> Moreover, do not the <hi>Pope,</hi> his <hi>Cardinals,</hi> the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and the reſt of your Romiſh fraternity abound in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:168420:36"/>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity learning?</hi> notwithſtanding which, do not you and the reſt in <hi>England,</hi> accuſe all thoſe <hi>learned</hi> ones, for <hi>wreſting the Scriptures</hi> to their own deſtruction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>38.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In what confuſion do your next Section ſhew you to live in? which you begin with as full an acknowledgment of the <hi>impotency</hi> of humane learning, to give the knowledge of the <hi>myſteries</hi> of the Kingdom, as I my ſelf have at any time, or could have made. Your words are theſe. <hi>We acknowledge that all the learning of the world will not bring ſaving truth effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally home to the underſtanding, and conſciences of men; nay, carnal reaſon, back'd with LEARNING, will diſpute the light of the moſt glorious doctrinal truths of the Goſpel, out of mens judgements, and the moſt glorious practical truths of of the Goſpel out of mens conſciences, as appears daily in thoſe, whoſe learning Satan makes uſe of</hi> (as he doth of yours and others) <hi>to defend, and patronize their luſts. So that there needs another kind of learning, to ſettle theſe truths ſavingly in the minds and hearts of men, which the Scripture calls the revelation and demonſtration of the Spirit.</hi> Thus are you conſtrained in words (whatever your hearts are) to give teſtimony to the <hi>inſufficiency</hi> of your Idol <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity learning,</hi> and to the <hi>efficacy</hi> of the <hi>revelation</hi> and <hi>demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Spirit.</hi> And yet in the cloſe of the ſame Section, you cannot but call <hi>Schools of learning, no ſmall props of Chriſtian Religion.</hi> Are not they very ſure props of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion,</hi> in which men learn that, which joyned with <hi>carnal reaſon will diſpute the moſt glorious truths of the Goſpel out of mens judgements and conſciences.</hi> Here is juſt the image of <hi>Babel.</hi> As your brethren do uſe to preach, ſo do you print; who oftentimes in their Sermons, do very zealouſly aſſert a thing for truth, and before they cloſe their diſcourſe, do croſs the ſame thing and contradict it. I could tell the Reader at large what precious Plants the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> and <hi>Schools</hi> of learning, do oftentimes nurſe up, but I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that untill another ſeaſon. Onely for cloſe of this, you
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:168420:36"/>being now crying Hoſanna to your Univerſities, let me ask you this queſtion; How came it to paſs that <hi>Simon Ford</hi> was (a very few years ſince) expelled the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Simon Ford</hi> turned out of the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </note> Was the <hi>Mother</hi> unrighteous, or was the <hi>Son</hi> wicked? If for a <hi>good</hi> deed he was driven thence, then that <hi>prop of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion,</hi> was a perſecuter of the <hi>innocent;</hi> if for <hi>evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing,</hi> then let the Reader judge, how well this man behaved himſelf there, that the Univerſity (which I am ſure here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore did rarely adminiſter expulſion to any, but for a very great crime) thought good to <hi>vomit</hi> him up as a <hi>corrupt</hi> member.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT.</hi> 40, 41, 42, 43.</head>
               <p>In the next place I cannot but take notice how much ſtir both you and <hi>William Thomas</hi> do make, about that expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mine in the Twelfth Article <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter preach'd that Goſpel which Chriſt by his Spirit revealed in them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2 10. Gal. 1.16.</note> And here you follow your old trade of making <hi>meanings</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my plain words: And you <hi>doubt another Snake in the graſs of this fair expreſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Are you Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, and know not to this day what it is to <hi>preach the Goſpel,</hi> which he hath <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Are there two Goſpels? or did <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> preach two, <hi>viz.</hi> one revealed <hi>in</hi> them and another <hi>without</hi> them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> there any other way of knowing the glorious myſteries of the Goſpel, but by revelation made by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of Ieſus <hi>within.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Thomas</hi> confeſſeth, that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed <hi>by immediate revelation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 44.</note> which (ſaith he) <hi>We are not ſo preſumptuous as to expect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Poor blind man! The Lord is, my witneſs, that my beart was moved with pitty towards him at the reading of this expeſſion, and could even weep over him thus drowned in ignorance. What hath he been preaching theſe <hi>thirty and nine years</hi> (for ſo long it ſeems he hath been a Teacher) who is ſo far from having received,<note place="margin">Pag. 8. confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> that he never expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:168420:37"/>
                  <hi>inſtruction by immediate revelation?</hi> Hath he only taught the hiſtory of that which others did, and ſpake? If ſo, what hath he done more then the Devils, and many (now) damned ſpirits, can do, and have done? Cannot thoſe ſoul ſpirits <hi>talk</hi> of what others have ſaid, and done in the Scriptures? nay,<note place="margin">Mark. 5.7.</note> do we not find an unclean ſpirit preaching Chriſt in <hi>words</hi> to be the <hi>Son of the moſt high God?</hi> Have not the <hi>Pope,</hi> his <hi>Cardinals</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites</hi> the knowledge of the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the <hi>Prophets, Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and do preach them in <hi>words?</hi> Had not the <hi>Prieſts, Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> the knowledge of the letter of Scriptures, and yet ſlew Chriſt? Could not <hi>Paul</hi> have preached the <hi>hiſtory</hi> of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that ſpake of Chriſt, even then (when with all his learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) he drew his blood, and perſecuted him from City to City? Now, what hath <hi>William Thomas</hi> done more then all theſe, unleſs, beſides the knowledge of the <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> gained by reading and hearing, he hath received <hi>instruction</hi> by the <hi>immediate revelation of the Spirit</hi> in the myſtery, as <hi>Paul</hi> afterwards did, and ſo come to know the ſame made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt which hath been hid from ages,<note place="margin">Col. 1.26, 27.</note> 
                  <hi>viz. Chriſt in</hi> him <hi>the hope of glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the manifeſtation of his ignorance,<note place="margin">Page 45.</note> he proceedeth in the next page to caſt up a loathſom morſel of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs, calling that expreſſion, of <hi>witneſſing the Saints conditions,</hi> by the reproachful name of <hi>gibberiſh.</hi> But let the ſcorner and the ſcoffer know, that though he <hi>preach</hi> and <hi>talk</hi> of the Saints words (which the evil Angels themſelves can do) until he drop into his grave, if he live and die a ſtranger to the <hi>Saints conditions,</hi> he will be found to be but a <hi>lyar</hi> before the Lord, in the great day of his account. He may go up in his Pulpit, and make many guilded Orations, about <hi>Pauls</hi> being <hi>crucified with Chriſt,</hi> and Chriſts <hi>living in him</hi> (if he will yet acknowledge that to be a truth) and yet, if he come not to witneſs the <hi>ſame condition</hi> of <hi>Pauls</hi> to be <hi>his,</hi> let me tell him, that when the Lamb cometh to judgement, he ſhall wiſh with tears, that he might indeed know that which his ſcornful pen now trampleth upon as <hi>gibberiſh.</hi> Miſerable ſouls, who paſs away their daies (and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:168420:37"/>ſo ſink into eternity) under ſuch mens teachings, who nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>have,</hi> nor <hi>expect</hi> to have <hi>inſtruction from the immediate revelation of the Spirit,</hi> and ſcornfully ſpurn at thoſe that <hi>witneſs the Saints conditions.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>43.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>You</hi> alſo have a ſtone to throw at this expreſſion, calling it odd and uncouth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> To thoſe that are ignorant of it, even the pearl of great price is of little value; and ſo it is to you, who live in blindneſs your ſelves, and do ſtrive to keep others bound in the ſame chain. And whereas you charge me in the cloſe of this Section, <hi>with ſpeaking ſcornfully of the righteouſneſs of Chriſt.</hi> I ſay you are a couple of impudent liars, who dare print that as mine, which never was in my heart to think, nor upon my lips to expreſs. Are you Miniſters of Chriſt, who can ſcarce write a leaf, without a lie? Beſide; the witneſs of God in my own conſcience,<note place="margin">Chriſts inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency pleaded againſt the cry of the Chief-Prieſts: Page. 55.</note> the honeſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may ſee that I have my own expreſſion as a witneſs for me alſo in my book, againſt your filthy ſtander? in which I ſpake of ſuch, <hi>as did talk of a righteouſneſs beyond the ſtars,</hi> and they in the mean time <hi>live in filthineſs and pollution,</hi> and is this to ſpeak <hi>ſcornfully of the righteouſneſs of Chriſt,</hi> when as it was not ſo much as mentioned? They that witneſs Chriſt <hi>in</hi> them, do not witneſs his righteouſneſs to be <hi>a far</hi> off from them, unleſs you ſuppoſe that Chriſt can be <hi>ſeparated</hi> from his righteouſneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>44.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Your next Section containeth little worthy of notice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you ſay, that if <hi>I mean as I ſay, then you mean and ſay as I do.</hi> And yet you cannot forbear to multiply words, and make a confeſſion of your faith; telling me, that you <hi>do not make</hi> your <hi>mortification of ſin, or reſurrection to newneſs of life, any part of your righteouſneſs in the preſence of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> You have little reaſon ſo to do; for that would be a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:168420:38"/>ſtrange <hi>polluted</hi> righteouſneſs to appear in the preſence of the Lord with, which is made up of ſuch <hi>mock-mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of ſin, and <hi>reſurrection</hi> to life, as <hi>yours</hi> is; who by your unclean fruits do make it manifeſt, that you are <hi>alive</hi> to ſin, and <hi>dead</hi> unto newneſs of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>45.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>You cannot forbear (being accuſtomed to it) to add a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother groſs lie, to the former, in the beginning of this Section alſo; averting that in my fourteenth Article, <hi>I do confeſs that I do both publiſh, and practiſe, an unmannerly diſreſpect of all perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Why ſirs, is the dread and fear of the Lord quite removed from before your eyes, that you are thus audacious in printing, and publiſhing, ſuch notorious <hi>untruths</hi> unto the world? did I, by my recital of the words of the Apoſtle <hi>James (he that reſpecteth perſons doth commit ſin) confeſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">James 2.9.</note> 
                  <hi>that I did both publiſh and practice an unmannerly diſreſpect of all perſons?</hi> Do you not lay the innocent Apoſtle under the ſame condemnation, ſince the words recited out of that Scripture, were originally <hi>his</hi> and not <hi>mine?</hi> as you have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pleaded hard for your <hi>backs</hi> and your <hi>bellies;</hi> ſo in this and your following Section, you do for your <hi>honour;</hi> being loth to loſe the <hi>cap</hi> and the <hi>knee,</hi> and <hi>greetings</hi> in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets. And having here (as formerly) laid a <hi>lie</hi> for your foundation, you proceed to tell me, that you will <hi>diſpute it with me, whether Religion doth deſtroy civility and good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners?</hi> A thing which I never aſſerted, and therefore is out of all queſtion with me. True Religion is the <hi>Nurſe,</hi> not the <hi>deſtroyer</hi> of <hi>good manners;</hi> which good manners do conſiſt, in doing the things that are honeſt both in the ſight of God and men; not in an Apiſh fantaſtical pulling off the <hi>hat,</hi> and crying, <hi>Your humble ſervant Sir;</hi> when as oftentimes whilſt that complement is upon the <hi>lip,</hi> there is ſo much malice in the <hi>heart,</hi> as would cut the throat of the perſon ſaluted, were there but an opportunity preſented.</p>
               <p>You proceed on and ſay, that you do <hi>humbly conceive
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:168420:38"/>that the fifth Commandment is not yet repealed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Did I ever ſay it was? What? always create images in your own corrupt fancies, and then contend about them? I ſay according to the Scriptures, that <hi>children</hi> ought to <hi>obey their</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Eph. 6.1.</note> 
                  <hi>parents, and ſervants their maſters,</hi> and all people the<note n="r" place="margin">Verſ. 5. Tit. 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>magiſtrates in the Lord.</hi> Which obedience conſiſteth in doing all things <hi>juſt,</hi> and well <hi>pleaſing in</hi> the ſight of God. Neither do I deny to call perſons, or things, <hi>noble, excellent,</hi> or <hi>honourable,</hi> which indeed are ſo. But what is this to your <hi>crouching,</hi> and <hi>cringing,</hi> and <hi>capping,</hi> and <hi>kneeing</hi> it, to the man <hi>wearing the gold ring,</hi> and the <hi>gay raiment;</hi> paſſing by the poor man in <hi>vile apparrel,</hi> without any notice or regard? And whereas you juſtifie your ſelves as ſuch who <hi>do prefer a godly poor man, before any wealthy man, that is not ſo.</hi> I ſay, how doth this appear? Is it by your <hi>inſulting</hi> and <hi>lording</hi> it over all thoſe in the Town of <hi>Redding,</hi> that refuſe to be Vaſſals to your corrupt wills and luſts? Let thoſe that are the <hi>godly poor</hi> in and about that Town, be witneſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you in what you have here falſly aſſerted of your ſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>47.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And whereas you demand of me, why I do <hi>give</hi> the name of <hi>Sirs,</hi> and <hi>Sir,</hi> ſince you ſay my <hi>brethren do quarrel with the name of Maſter,</hi> or <hi>Sir.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, that for the Readers ſake,<note place="margin">Acts 7.26. "ΑΝΔΡΕΣ <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>VIRI.</hi> Act. 27.10. "ΑΝΔΡΕΣ <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Viri vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo.</hi> Ver 25. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> "ΑΝΔΡΕΣ <hi>Bono animo eſtote VIRI.</hi> So verſ. 21.</note> I ſhall give this plain account thereof; I do uſe the word <hi>Sir,</hi> and <hi>Sirs,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> uſed it, and as <hi>Paul</hi> uſed it three times in one Chapter, to expreſs no more then <hi>man,</hi> or <hi>men,</hi> for ſo you do well know (though you conceal it from your Reader) the word there uſed doth ſignifie, and no more. And whereas you ſay that my <hi>brethren might know how often the word Maſter,</hi> or <hi>Sir, is given and taken by the Apoſtles of Chriſt.</hi> I ſay, I find not in Scripture that ever any Apoſtle of Chriſt gave the word <hi>Maſter,</hi> to any <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> or other <hi>Saint,</hi> nor that any Apoſtle did uſe the title of <hi>Sir,</hi> or <hi>Sirs,</hi> to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles or other Saints, by the word (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>Kurie,</hi> or (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>)
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:168420:39"/>
                  <hi>Kurioi,</hi> which words do expreſs <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> or <hi>Maſterſhip;</hi> but when they did uſe the word <hi>Sirs,</hi> it was by the Greek word, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>Andres,</hi> which ſignifieth no more then <hi>men,</hi> and ſo do I uſe it, and no otherwiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>48.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>You have not yet done with this. But do go on to <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe worſe blood in my veins, then that which boyles againſt poor Miniſters.</hi> And you <hi>doubt that I that would ſtrip them</hi> (viz. the Magiſtrates) <hi>of their Titles,</hi> have too great mind to their Offices.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Are you come with this threed-bare ſuggeſtion again? <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and his Miniſters throughout all ages, did cleave cloſe to the <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Prieſts pretend great love to the Magiſtrates whilſt they will ſerve them.</note> whilſt they would be their <hi>ſervants,</hi> and <hi>ſupporters;</hi> but when they would no longer <hi>ſerve</hi> their <hi>luſts,</hi> then <hi>damn</hi> them to the bottomleſs pit: Fain you would perſwade the Magiſtrates what <hi>aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> perſons, the people called Quakers are; which cannot be prevalent with any, but ſuch as are as drunk with <hi>rage</hi> againſt them as your ſelves; unleſſe it be becauſe they are a people <hi>trodden down</hi> by all as <hi>mire</hi> in the ſtreets. But let me ask you Did the Quakers ever attempt the <hi>overthrow</hi> and <hi>deſtruction</hi> of any power that would not eſtabliſh them in the <hi>throne?</hi> Or did they ever endeavour to bring into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> an army of <hi>Scots,</hi> to over-awe both <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> into ſubjection to preſcripts, and rules of their creating? ſuch things as theſe (with many other that I omit) would have ſhewed ſome bad <hi>blood running in their veins indeed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do well remember the time when your Pulpits ſounded of little elſe, but <hi>Curſe ye Meroz, curſe bitterly the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof,</hi> &amp;c. ſtirring up the people to joyn with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, againſt the late <hi>King,</hi> and your forefathers the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops;</hi> hoping that the Parliament in concluſion (Biſhops be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dethroned) would have made you <hi>heirs</hi> of their <hi>inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> of their <hi>lands,</hi> and <hi>revenues,</hi> of their <hi>honour, vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> and <hi>domination;</hi> and have committed the <hi>ſcepter</hi> to you, to rule and <hi>tyrannize,</hi> over all other mens <hi>conſciences.</hi> But
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:168420:39"/>they denying you that, your <hi>Dialect</hi> touching them was ſoon changed in your Pulpits: and probably, had you not been timely prevented, you bad given them in requital for all their pains and travel, nought but a <hi>Scottiſh yoak.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>49.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In this Section you do not a little <hi>inſult,</hi> and <hi>triumph,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a great <hi>flouriſh,</hi> as if you had gained ſome notable <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</hi> And all becauſe in my laſt Article, I ſaid, that the people called Quakers, did <hi>avouch it proper,</hi> as in <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latine, ſo in Engliſh, to ſay thou, and thee, to any ſingle perſon.</hi> And was this ſuch a groundwork for you to build ſo mighty a <hi>flouriſh</hi> upon? Can you and your <hi>ſchool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boy of ten years old,</hi> (you ſpeak of) find me any place in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture where the Hebrew word, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or the Greek word. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or the Latine word. <hi>Tu,</hi> are rendred any otherwiſe in Engliſh then <hi>THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>?</hi> Or can you, and your young Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, ſhew me any place in Scripture, where the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or the Latine word <hi>vos,</hi> are rendred any otherwiſe, then <hi>you,</hi> or <hi>ye?</hi> Neither am I ſo <hi>ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> (as you are pleaſed to call me) but that I do well know, that words in all languages do ſignifie <hi>this,</hi> or <hi>that, (ex in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituto humano)</hi> by mans <hi>inſtitutior,</hi> but when by mans inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, <hi>tu</hi> is appointed to ſignifie <hi>thou,</hi> and <hi>vos, ye,</hi> I hope its not left <hi>(ad arbitrium)</hi> to every man to expreſſe <hi>ye,</hi> by the word <hi>tu,</hi> nor <hi>thou,</hi> by the word <hi>vos.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>50.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And becauſe you would not be left without ſome reaſon, why you ſay <hi>thou</hi> and <hi>thee, to the great God;</hi> you offer ſuch a one as you have, though it be a pittifull lame one, <hi>(viz.) becauſe you addreſs your ſelves to God in Prayer, in the unity of his nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Is it not proper upon the ſame ground to ſay <hi>thou</hi> and <hi>thee</hi> to a ſingle perſon? unleſs you will ſay that you ſpeak to a <hi>plurality</hi> of men, when you ſpeak but to <hi>one.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:168420:40"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Thomas</hi> ſaith, that to ſay <hi>thou,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Page 47.</note> and <hi>thee, to our ſuperiours is offenſive, which ought to be avoided?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Is that language <hi>offenſive</hi> unto <hi>men,</hi> which he himſelf doth give to the <hi>great God,</hi> as often as he prayeth? or is not the Lord of heaven and earth his Superior? if he be, why doth he not avoid ſuch offenſive language? And if to uſe the words <hi>thou</hi> and <hi>thee,</hi> be to be a <hi>perfect Clown</hi> (as he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it) then what would he be eſteemed, who doth publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſe the ſame to the Almighty God his Superiour ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in his Pulpit?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
               <head>SECT. <hi>54.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And now I am come to your large liſt of Particulars, which you call <hi>THE Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AKERS DOCTRINES:</hi> In muſtering up which you have ſhewed your ſelves not a little <hi>fraudulent</hi> and <hi>diſ-ingenuous:</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>For firſt, upon diligent ſearch and enquiry, I can ſcarce find one particular in the whole Catalogue (that is, of any weight) but is either a thing <hi>created,</hi> or <hi>miſquoted.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, Let the Reader obſerve whoſe teſtimony you offer in evidence to prove thoſe things of which you accuſe them <hi>(viz.)</hi> The Book called <hi>The Perfect Phariſee, John Toldervy, Richard Baxter,</hi> &amp;c. If <hi>Pilate</hi> will accept of the teſtimony of the whole counſell of the <hi>Rulers, chief Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> againſt Chriſt (to whom they were profeſſed enemies) can he be adjudged to be any other then a perſon worthy to ſuffer death? If a <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite</hi> ſhould come to one of you and impeach you, and thoſe called <hi>Proteſtants</hi> for <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and for proof there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſhould offer in evidence, the teſtimony of the <hi>Pope, Cardinals,</hi> and the whole <hi>Romiſh crew,</hi> would you judge it <hi>fair dealing,</hi> or would you not reject ſuch his proof as coming from thoſe that are <hi>judges</hi> and <hi>parties</hi> againſt you?</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, if the things you charge were all true, (as they are not) muſt the particular expreſſion of one man be preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:168420:40"/>charged as the <hi>doctrine</hi> of many <hi>thouſands</hi> that are called by the ſame name, who do utterly diſown the things ſo ſpoken? If this be a regular way of proceeding, what Monſters of men could I ſoon prove you two to be, and moſt of the publike Teachers of the Nation, by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>wicked, prophane, blaſphemous expreſſions</hi> of your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and followers?</item>
               </list>
               <p>Nay farther, if I liſted to charge all that upon you two, which I have heard from the mouths of ſober men, nay, which I find <hi>printed</hi> touching (not your <hi>ſayings</hi> only; but) the wickedneſs of your <hi>doings,</hi> you would appear ſo foul and filthy, that there is no honeſt heart but would diſ-own your fellowſhip (without repentance) whilſt he had a day to live.</p>
               <p>Its not my buſineſs not is it my purpoſe, to contend about other mens words. Yet that the Reader may judge how you deal with the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> in the reſt of your Articles: I ſhall let him know how <hi>falſely</hi> and <hi>unfairly,</hi> you deal with them in two or three of the Particulars:</p>
               <p n="1">1. One of the Quakers Doctrines you ſay is, <hi>That they are equall with God, as holy, juſt, and good, as God himſelf.</hi> For proof of which you quote the Book called, <hi>The Perfect Phariſee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> 1. The two perſons upon whom this expreſſion was charged have publikely enough denied, and diſowned it in Print. 2. I do not know any one perſon that is called a Quaker, but doth (as I my ſelf do) <hi>deny</hi> and <hi>abhor</hi> any ſuch expreſſion. Now then, let the honeſt Reader obſerve, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not a wicked and a horrible thing in theſe mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious perſons, to charge that as one of the Quakers <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,</hi> which not only the perſons, on whom it is <hi>fathered</hi> do deny, and diſown; but alſo, which is with one lip <hi>deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and <hi>diſowned,</hi> by every individual among thoſe many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands that are called by that <hi>name</hi> in theſe Nations.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Next you ſay that one of our <hi>ſhee-Quakers being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented before the Major of your Town, and asked what ſhee was, and what was her name</hi> (which is your falſe and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed addition) <hi>roundly anſwered, I am that I am.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:168420:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> I have throughly examined this matter to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, and do find it to be like your former, a filthy ſlander and a falſhood. For the ſaid perſon being again, and again asked by the Mayor, <hi>What ſhe was</hi> (not <hi>what was her name,</hi> at that time ſhe gave the following anſwer) anſwered, <hi>I am what I am.</hi> And to this I have the teſtimony of two credible perſons that were then preſent. And whereas you mention two Officers of your Town that will <hi>atteſt</hi> what you ſay <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on oath.</hi> I ſay, to convince thoſe two perſons either of the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of their memories, or the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of their hearts, let them remember (and let the Reader take notice of it) that ſhe being accuſed for ſaying, <hi>I am what I am,</hi> a ſtander by asked, why, did not <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, <hi>by the grace of God. I am what I am?</hi> Ay, replied the Mayor <hi>by the grace of God?</hi> But if ſhe had ſaid,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>I am that I am</hi> (which ſhe did not) muſt the ſaying of one particular perſon be made preſently one of the <hi>Quakers Doctrines?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Another Doctrine of the Quakers you ſay (in your fourteenth Section) is, <hi>That whoſoever expecteth to be ſaved by him that died at Jeruſalem, ſhall be deceived.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rep.</hi> Bluſh and be aſhamed (if you can) ye ſhameleſs liars; who durſt in print avouch that for one of the <hi>Quakers Doctrines,</hi> which is publickly diſowned by them; as all may ſee who will but peruſe their ſeveral Books. And where I have been at their meetings, I have often heard the thing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned in the hearing of many hundreds of people; and ſalvation owned and preſented, by <hi>none</hi> other but by that very Son of God, that <hi>witneſſed a good confeſſion before Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilat,</hi> and <hi>offered</hi> himſelf upon the <hi>croſs</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for the <hi>ſins</hi> of the world. The <hi>Accuſer of the brethren,</hi> which ruleth in you, taught you to be ſo maliciouſly ſubtle, that you quoted no proof for this abominable ſlander, and therefore the lie yet reſteth upon your own heads. And if you can produce any perſon that avoucheth any ſuch thing, know, that all the people called Quakers that I know, are as ready to <hi>deny</hi> and <hi>diſown</hi> him, as they are to deny the filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſuch falſe accuſers as <hi>you</hi> two are.</p>
               <p>I am unwilling any longer to detain the ſober Reader,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:168420:41"/>whilſt I rake further into that filthy <hi>dunghil</hi> of your <hi>untruths,</hi> and <hi>ſlanders.</hi> By what hath been already ſaid to thoſe three particulars, he may eaſily judge of what ſtamp the remainer are, which are compriſed in that deformed Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</p>
               <p>And now ſince you judge it equal to take the particular expreſſions (and thoſe for the moſt part not true, but invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) of certain perſons called Quakers, and charge them as <hi>Doctrines</hi> upon the whole <hi>body</hi> of that people that are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſame name; I hope you will not eſteem it otherwiſe then <hi>juſt</hi> to have better meaſure returned back to you, then you have meaſured unto others, <hi>viz.</hi> by preſenting the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with ſuch expreſſions, as have dropt from the lips and pens of one of your brethren, which (according to your own rule) you muſt give me leave to call</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Prieſts Doctrines,</head>
               <p n="1">1. That to <hi>affirm that Chriſt is the means, and that there is no other means of ſalvation, is an error, if not damnable. Joſh. Miller</hi> of <hi>Cardiff</hi> in his book entituled, <hi>Antichriſt in man the Quakers Idol,</hi> pag. 13. Did the people cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Quakers, preach and profeſs ſuch devilliſh Doctrine as this, I would diſown them in the face of the whole world.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That lying is no ſin but a change of the mind.</hi> Aſſerted and pleaded for by the ſame <hi>Joſhuah Miller</hi> of <hi>Cardiff,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſufficient witneſs ready to atteſt it. A wicked principle! and an in-let to all <hi>fraud, deceit,</hi> and <hi>falſs-witneſs-bearing,</hi> and that which being practiſed would turn all the converſe of men (which ought to be managed with truth as in the preſence of the Lord) into a continued <hi>lye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many more particulars I could reckon up, and prove,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:168420:42"/>upon your ſelves, and ſome of your Function, of as deep a die as theſe two. But I ſhall ſpare you for the preſent. Onely let me adviſe you, that if your way of proceeding againſt the people called Quakers be <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>reaſonable,</hi> in throwing <hi>created</hi> and <hi>miſquoted</hi> expreſſions, as dirt upon the whole body of that people; I know not how you and all the publick Teachers of the Nation will be able to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve your ſelves, from being horrible <hi>Blaſphemers</hi> of the name of Chriſt, and <hi>deſtroyers</hi> of the beauty of all humane converſe.</p>
               <p>Thus have I made my Reply to that part of your Pamphlet that concerneth my Epiſtle. To the after part thereof (wherein you rather <hi>ſeek</hi> matter of quarrel with me, then anſwer ought that concerned you) I ſhall not be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in making a particular return, in caſe I hear not further from <hi>William Thomas,</hi> whom that do more eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern.</p>
               <p>In the mean while return into your ſelves, and conſider what you are now doing, and whoſe <hi>errand</hi> you are poſting upon: And know that neither you, not your <hi>weapons</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med againſt the Lamb ſhall proſper before the Lord. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider whether Satan doth not make the ſame uſe of <hi>your learning,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In your 38. Section.</note> which you confeſs he doth of ſome mens, <hi>viz. To defend and patronize your luſts.</hi> You may for a ſeaſon, with <hi>fair</hi> words, and <hi>ſpecious</hi> pretences, deceive the <hi>ſimple;</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading them that you are <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe you preach and profeſs him in words, though you <hi>perſecute</hi> and <hi>crucifie</hi> him where he appeareth in power. But though men may be <hi>deceived,</hi> yet <hi>God will not be mocked.</hi> As you <hi>ſow,</hi> ſo ſhall you alſo <hi>reap.</hi> Whilſt you <hi>ſow</hi> to the fleſh, bringing forth the <hi>corrupt</hi> fruits of <hi>Pride, Envy, Covetouſneſs, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, &amp;c.</hi> It is not your guilded profeſſion that will cover you over in the preſence of the moſt high God. In the <hi>pure</hi> light of Chriſt, that <hi>deſpiſed</hi> light, that light which you ſo furiouſly <hi>decry</hi> and <hi>trample</hi> upon, ſearch and prove your ſelves. For I bear record to it (and you ſhall one day witneſs the ſame to be true) that a ſwift and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:168420:42"/>witneſs will it be againſt all tranſgreſſors, in the <hi>great</hi> and terrible <hi>day of the Lord.</hi> It will then aſſuredly ſpeak, by no gift will it be <hi>bribed,</hi> nor by the tongue of an Orator, will it be enjoyned <hi>ſilence;</hi> but an impartial cry will it make before the Lord for <hi>juſtice</hi> upon the the evil doer, and he himſelf ſhall put his ſeal to it, that the cry thereof is <hi>juſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am <hi>A Friend to your</hi> Souls, <hi>but an unalterable Enemy to your</hi> deceit. THOMAS SPEED.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:168420:43"/>
            <head>A TESTIMONY FOR TRUTH, AND A Caution to all that profeſs it.</head>
            <p>TO live in the <hi>fear</hi> of the Lord, is the <hi>beginning</hi> of true <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> from which whoſoever departeth, doth at once loſe both his <hi>Rock</hi> &amp; his <hi>glory.</hi> Whilſt the <hi>earthen</hi> veſſel is made the habitation of the <hi>Lord,</hi> it is all beautiful, and in <hi>him,</hi> and for <hi>his</hi> ſake, to be honored among the Saints; but he being withdrawn, what is man, but <hi>a dark</hi> temple of clay, whence the <hi>glory</hi> is <hi>depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi> Man abiding in the <hi>truth,</hi> ſhineth as a Star in the Firmament, but turning his back upon <hi>that,</hi> he becometh an unſavory
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:168420:43"/>ſnuff whoſe light is <hi>extinguiſhed.</hi> Whilſt <hi>Aaron</hi> liſtneth to the <hi>Lord,</hi> I will hearken unto <hi>him;</hi> but when he giveth ear to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing charms of the <hi>people,</hi> to make <hi>new Gods,</hi> I will leave both him and them to worſhip <hi>the molten Calf,</hi> which he hath ſet up. How illuſtrious is the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> while he abideth <hi>faithful</hi> with the <hi>God of his Fathers?</hi> but forſaking <hi>him,</hi> and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto <hi>ſtrange women,</hi> his <hi>wiſdom</hi> becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>fooliſhneſs;</hi> his <hi>ſtrength, weakneſs,</hi> and is brought by the ſubtilty of the Tempter to bow his knee to thoſe <hi>dead Idols, Aſhte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roth</hi> and <hi>Milcom;</hi> But the true God, whom <hi>Aaron</hi> once ſerved, is not to be <hi>blaſphemed,</hi> becauſe <hi>he</hi> is <hi>now</hi> found ſacrificing to an <hi>Idol.</hi> Neither will the <hi>wholeſom</hi> words given forth by the mouth of <hi>Solomon</hi> from the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the Lord, ceaſe to be truth throughout all generations, though <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> heart be <hi>turned</hi> from his God, and he prevailed upon to worſhip thoſe things that are <hi>no Gods.</hi> Curſed be that <hi>lip</hi> that ſpeaketh evil of the <hi>pure light</hi> of the Lord, becauſe ſome <hi>ſtarting</hi> from it, are found wandring in the perillous paths of <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:168420:44"/>They that <hi>abide</hi> in the light, walk <hi>ſafely,</hi> but who ſo <hi>turneth</hi> from it, walketh among the <hi>rocks.</hi> Who is he that deſpiſeth the light of a <hi>candle</hi> in a dark night, becauſe another who <hi>turneth</hi> from it, <hi>ſtumbleth</hi> and <hi>falleth?</hi> Or where is he among all the Sons of men, that will refuſe to walk in a <hi>clean</hi> path, becauſe ſome <hi>ſtraying</hi> from it, are found having their feet <hi>ſtock'd</hi> in the mire and clay? Look well therefore to your ſtanding all ye that fear the Lord; and whilſt ye <hi>think</hi> ye <hi>ſtand, take heed leaſt ye fall.</hi> Let not your faith ſtand in the <hi>wiſdom</hi> or <hi>excellency of man,</hi> but in the <hi>power</hi> of the Lord: Walk <hi>humbly</hi> with your God, ſo will you walk ſafely. Forſake not the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed fruit of the tree of <hi>life,</hi> to eat of the <hi>ſhining</hi> fruit of the tree of <hi>Knowledge. Stumble</hi> not, becauſe another <hi>falleth,</hi> but be the more watchful over your own ſteps. And to all you that rejoyce at anothers ſwerving from the truth, I ſay, beware how you condemn Chriſt for a <hi>deceiver,</hi> or his doctrine for <hi>deceit,</hi> becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> denied him. If <hi>Peter</hi> return to himſelf, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, <hi>his</hi> will be the <hi>joy,</hi> but <hi>yours</hi> the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:168420:44"/>
               <hi>ſhame.</hi> What gain will it be to you, O ye men <hi>unwiſe,</hi> if over one that is fallen, you your ſelves <hi>ſtumble</hi> and <hi>fall</hi> to your own <hi>deſtruction?</hi> He may be <hi>raiſed</hi> by power of the Lord to praiſe him in the <hi>Land of the living,</hi> when as you, being <hi>hardned</hi> by the ſliding of <hi>his</hi> feet will be <hi>ſealed</hi> up under the chains of eternal dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
